<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox plebis, or, The peoples out-cry against oppression, injustice, and tyranny. Wherein the liberty of the subject is asserted, Magna Charta briefly but pithily expounded. Lieutenant Colonell Lilburne's sentence published and refuted. Committees arraigned, goalers condemned, and remedies provided.</title>
            <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O636A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E362_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 58:E362[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox plebis, or, The peoples out-cry against oppression, injustice, and tyranny. Wherein the liberty of the subject is asserted, Magna Charta briefly but pithily expounded. Lieutenant Colonell Lilburne's sentence published and refuted. Committees arraigned, goalers condemned, and remedies provided.</title>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the sitting of Parliament; during which time the presse ought to be free and open, as the Parliament declared to the bishops at the beginning thereof,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed 1646. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Overton by Wing.</note>
                  <note>[2] p. at end = "The publisher to the reader", which notes two of Lilburnes' books and which includes errata.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 19th. London 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Freedom of the press --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:113893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>VOX PLEBIS, OR, The Peoples Out-cry Againſt Oppreſsion, Injuſtice, and Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein the Liberty of the Subject is aſſerted,</hi> Magna Charta <hi>briefly but pithily expounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lieutenant Colonell LILBURNES Sentence publiſhed and refuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Committees arraigned, Goalers condemned, and remedies provided..</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAI. 10. 1. 2.</bibl>
               <p>Woe unto them that decree unrighteous Decrees, and that write grievouſneſſe which they have preſcribed:</p>
               <p>To turn away the needy from judgoment, and to take away the right from the poore of my people, that Widowes may be their prey, and that they may rob the Fatherleſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>JER. 22. 15. 16. 17.</bibl>
               <p>Shalt thou reign, becauſe thou cloſeſt thy ſelfe in Cedar? Did not thy Father eat and drinke, and doe judgement and juſtice, and then it was well with him?</p>
               <p>He judged the cauſe of the poore and needy, then it was well with him: was not this to know me, ſaith the Lord?</p>
               <p>But thine eyes and thine heart are not, but for thy covetouſneſſe, and for to ſhed innocent blood, and for oppreſſion and violence to doe it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London printed 1646. in the ſitting of Parliament; during which time the Preſſe ought to be free and open, as the Parliament declared to the Biſhops at the beginning thereof.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:113893:2"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113893:2"/> ALL States in the beginning are venerable: That Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique which would ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p it ſelfe from ruine, is above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to keep their Religion uncorrupted, and their Lawes from violation
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or as true Religion is the tie of the Conſcience to obedience and obſervation of juſt Lawes (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as have their foundation in Divine Authority;) So are good Lawes the civill ſanctions or ſinewes of a Common-wealth, that bind the members thereof together by the execution of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and piety, in a perpetuall bond of peace and tranquillity. So that if either Religion be neglected, or the Lawes violated; the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of that Common-wealth muſt needs be neere, where ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects are found. But where Religion is held in due reverenee, and the ancient Lawes of that Common-wealth are inviolably kept; the Governors of ſuch a State, ſhall eaſily keep their Common-wealth religious; and conſequently, virtuous, and united. Now there is no better way to make the Subjects of a State good, and to incline them to virtue; then that thoſe that ſit at the Helm of that State, and have the government thereof, ſhould hold forth cleare examples of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and juſtice, in their own lives and actions, to the people under their government; eſpecially in the adminiſtration of Lawes. For as hunger and poverty make men laborious; ſo Lawes duly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, make them good: and good examples proceed from good education; and good education, from the due, obſervance of ſetled Lawes. Of all humane Lawes, there is none more fit to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, then thoſe that concern our Lives and Liberties. For thoſe that concern our Lives, they are moſt carefully, &amp; with the greateſt pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and circumſpection, to be executed: ſince if our lives bee taken away by injuſtice, death being
<hi>ultimum ſupplicium,</hi> the laſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this world; our injuries are remedileſſe and irrecoverable. Therefore we may irrefragably conclude, That Governours of a State ought to be very wary in judging of matters of life, and not in one tittle to deviate or depart from the known Lawes of the Land, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113893:3"/> leſt by committing of irrepairable wrongs upon the perſons of their innocent ſubjects; they draw Gods irreco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cileable vengeance upon themſelves, in that day when he ſhall viſit the Judges of the earth, and make inquiſition for the blood of his people, ſpilt by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, violence, and oppreſſion: which hee will ſurely doe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own everlaſting promiſe, and eternall decree, to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon all States to the end of the world: And as he did execute it upon <hi>Ahab,</hi> and his poſterity, and upon <hi>Jezebel</hi> his wife, for the unjuſt taking laway of the blood of <hi>Naboth,</hi> as you may read, 1 <hi>Kings 21. chap. 2 Kings 9. chap.</hi> concerning
<hi>Jehoram</hi> and <hi>Ieze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel:</hi> and in divers other inſtances evidenced unto us by the holy Scriptures. That which <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Agag,</hi> King of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites, As thy ſword hath made other women childleſſe; ſo ſhall thy mother be childleſſe among other women;</hi> hath a perpetuall morall uſe in Gods juſtice. For we may finde a thouſand examples where thoſe Princes, or States, which have ſold the blood of their people at a low rate; have made but the market for their enemies to buy of theirs at the ſame price. For it was never yet ſeen, that thoſe that dipt their hands in innocent blood, went dry to their graves; the blood that is unjuſtly ſpilt being not again gathered up from the ground by repetance. Theſe medicines miniſtred to the dead, have but dead rewards. Now as the Lawes concerning life, or proceedings therein, ought not to be Arbitrary; much more concerning liberty. For that the laws that concern the liberty of the ſubject, in reſpect of their object, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the whole body of the people, are far more large then thoſe which concern life: which lawes are onely relative to offenders, and guilty perſons, and not directly to the whole people; and therefore with the more tender regard to the ſubject, to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. Wherefore all manner of proceedings whatſoever, which are Arbitrary, and that tend to the taking away of our liberty, are moſt dangerous &amp; deſtructive to the State where ſuch are put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For Governours of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealths ought to know this, That at the ſame inſtant they begin to break the Lawes, and to execute an Arbitrary power upon the peoples liberties; at that very inſtant they begin to loſe their State. For by ſo doing, the Governours draw the <hi>Odium</hi> of the people upon them: and incite the people to find out and invent wayes unuſuall, and of innovation, to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their oppreſſors, and the execution of ſuch tyrannicall <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113893:3"/> power. It is a moſt ſure Rule in State policy, That all the Lawes that are made infavour of liberty, ſpring firſt from the diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people with their Governours. Whoſoever therefore ſits at the Helme of a State, bee it either a Common-wealth, or Principality; ſhould conſider before they execute any Arbitrary power upon the peoples liberties, what contrary times, by the ill effects of it, may come upon them; and what men in their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles they may ſtand in need of: and therefore ſhould live with them alwayes in ſuch manner, that upon any accident chancing; they may find them ready and willing to ſerve their occaſions. For in a Common-wealth well governed, it is to be deſired, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould chance, which may call in the uſe of extraordinary courſes. For though an extraordinary way, in ſome particular caſe, doe good; yet the example proves of ill conſequence, and will ſtirre the peoples minds to Jealouſie and Commotions; eſpecially when it concernes the publique liberty, and with that deep impreſſion, that having once freed themſelves from the oppreſſion of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours; it commonly falls out, that the State determines with the lives of the Governours. For the people bite more fiercely after they have recovered their liberty, then whlle they have continually main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it: And having once gotten poſſeſſion of their ancient rights, they will watch them ſo carefully, and with ſuch ſtrength and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, as that they will hardly be ſurprized again, or their rights any more wreſted from them. As it fell out in the caſe of the <hi>Romane</hi> State, when the <hi>Romanes</hi> having freed themſelves of the government of the <hi>Tarquins,</hi> their hertditary Kings; the Nobility began to take upon the the rule of the people: &amp; by the exerciſe of the like or greater tyrany the the <hi>Tarquins</hi> had done; the people being inforced by a neceſſity of their preſervations; created
<hi>Tribunes,</hi> as <hi>Guardians</hi> of the publick liberty, whereby the inſolence and Arbitrary power of the Nobilty, was reſtrained, and the people re-eſtated in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient liberty: which continued inviolable to them for the ſpace of 800. yeares (after 300. yeares oppreſſion of the Nobility,) to the great honour and renown of their Nation, and exceding enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Common-wealth. Now as concerning the liberty which the people of this Common-wealth, doe, and of right both divine and humane, ought to challenge; it conſiſts of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars following, Liberty of conſcience in matters of Faith, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113893:4"/> worſhip; Liberty of the Perſon, and liberty of Eſtate: which conſiſts properly in the propriety of their goods, and a diſpoſing power of their poſſeſſions. As touching liberty of Conſcience, it is due of Divine right to the people of God; ſince that the conſcience is a Divine impreſſion, or illumination, in the ſoule of man, which God inſtills into the heart by faith, whereby man is inſtructed to worſhip him in Spirit and Truth: and it is (as it were) the ingraven Character of the mind &amp; wil of God in the ſoul of man; not paſſive, nor conſiſting of bodily ſubſtance: therefore it is not to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, or inforced to ſubmit to any other rule, then what the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, by his revealed will, according to the Scriptures, hath imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in it: And for that cauſe is onely to bee accountable to him, whoſe image it is; as being the onely competent Judge of his owne will. As touching the liberty of our perſons: That is founded not onely in Divine Law, but in Nature ulſo; and as protected by the municipicall and known Lawes of this Kingdom. For as God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted every man free in <hi>Adam:</hi> ſo by nature are all alike freemen born; and are ſince made free in grace by Chriſt: no guilt of the parent being of ſufficiency to deprive the child of this freedome. And although there was that wicked and unchriſtian-like cuſtome of villany introduced by the
<hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour; yet was it but a violent uſurpation upon the Law of our Creation, Nature, and the ancient Lawes of this Kingdome: and is now, ſince the clearer light of the Goſpel hath ſhined forth, by a neceſſary harmony of humane ſociety; quite aboliſhed, as a thing odious both to God and man in this our Chriſtian Common-wealth. Now that the liberty of mens perſons hath ever been a thing moſt pretious in the eyes of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors and right deare and of moſt tender regard in the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and protection of the Law, if we doe but conſider the originall Lawes of this Realme, the proceedings of our Anceſtors, in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition and defence of their juſt liberties, and the continuall vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of them in making and ordaining good Lawes for their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary preſervation; we ſhall eaſily find that there hath not been any earthly thing or more weighty and important care to them, then the preſervation of their Liberties. To prove this, <hi>Andrew Horn,</hi> a learned man in the ancient Lawes of this Kingdome, in his Booke called, <hi>The Marrow of Juſtice,</hi> written in the reigne of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt,
<hi>fol.</hi> 1. ſaith,
<q rend="margQuotes">That after God had abated the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113893:4"/> of the <hi>Brittons,</hi> he did deliver the Realm to men more humble and ſimple, of the Countries adjoyning, to wit, the
<hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which came from the parts of <hi>Almaigne,</hi> to conquer this Land: of which men, there were <hi>fourty Soveraignes,</hi> which did rule as Companions; and thoſe Princes did call this Realme <hi>England,</hi> which before was named, <hi>The Greater Britaine.</hi> Theſe, after great warres, tribulations, and pains, by long time ſuffered; did chooſe <hi>amongst them, a King to reigne over them,</hi> to governe the people of God, and to maintain and defend their perſons, and their goods in quiet, by the Rules of Right, and <hi>at the beginning they did cauſe him to ſweare</hi> to maintaine the holy Chriſtian Faith, and to guide his people by right, with all his power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, and to obſerve the Lawes. And after, when the Kingdome was turned into an <hi>Heritage;</hi> King
<hi>Alfred,</hi> that governed this Kingdome about 174. yeares before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, did cauſe the great men of the Kingdome to aſſemble at
<hi>London,</hi> and there did ordain for a perpetuall uſage, <hi>That twice in the yeare, or oftner, if need ſhould be,</hi> in time of peace; they ſhould aſſemble at <hi>London</hi> in Parliament, for the government of Gods people, that men might live in quiet, and receive right, by certain uſages, and holy judgements. In which Parliament (faith our Authour) the rights and prerogatives of the Kings, and of the Subjects, are diſtinguiſhed, and ſet apart, and particularly by him expreſſed, too tedious here to inſert. Amongſt which Ordinances, we find, That no man ſhould be impriſoned but for a capitall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And if a man ſhould detain another in priſon by colour of right, (where there was none) till the party impriſoned died; hee that kept him in priſon ſhould bee held guilty of murder, as you may read pag. 33. And pag. 36. hee is declared guilty of homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, by whom a man ſhall die in priſon, whether it be the
<hi>Judges</hi> that ſhall too long delay to do a man right, or by cruelty of Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or ſuffering him to die of <hi>Famine:</hi> Or when a man that is adjudged to doe penance, ſhall be ſurcharged by his Goaler, with Irons, or other pain, whereby he is deprived of his life. And pag. 140. That by the ancient Law of <hi>England,</hi> it was Felony <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a man in priſon after ſufficient Baile offered,</hi> where the party was pleviſable. Every perſon was pleviſable, but hee that was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed of <hi>Treaſon, Murder, Robbery,</hi> or <hi>Burglary,</hi> pag. 35.</q> 
               <hi>None</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113893:5"/> 
               <hi>ought to be put in the common priſon, but onely ſuch at were AT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINTED, or principally APPEALED, or INDIC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED of ſome capitall offence, or</hi> ATTAINTED <hi>of falſe and wrongful impriſonment.</hi> So tender hath the ancient Lawes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of this Realme been of the liberty of their Subjects per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; That no man ought to be impriſoned but for a <hi>Capitall offence,</hi> as <hi>Treaſon, Murder, Robbery,</hi> or
<hi>Burglary.</hi> And, if for theſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; yet ought he to be let to Baile: which to deny, were felony, in caſe the priſoner were pleviſable, which is, if he were not <hi>appealed, indicted,</hi> or <hi>attainted.</hi> Nay, you ſee it was Felony to detain a man in priſon by colour of right, when there was none. Neitherwas the law tender of the perſons of Innocents, &amp; bailable perſons only; but alſo of the perſons of men not pleviſable and indicted: inſomuch that they ought not to be oppreſſed by their <hi>Judges</hi> or <hi>Goalers,</hi> upon pain of Felony. This cauſed our Author to complain in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, that thoſe good Lawes were
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: in theſe words, <hi>It is an abuſe that Goalers are ſuffered to ſpoyle and oppreſſe their priſoners, or to take ought from them, ſave their Armour and Weapons.</hi> Nu. 52. <hi>It is an abuſion that priſoners are put in Irons, or to other pain, before they are attainted of Felony.</hi> Nu. 5. <hi>It is an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſion to impriſon any other man then he that is indicted or appealed of Felony,</hi> in caſe he want not pledges, or mainpernours, pag. 289 And that this was the Law; is very clear: for that King <hi>Alfred</hi> did cauſe
<hi>Fourty four Juſtices in one year to be hanged for breach of theſe Lawes.</hi> And more particularly the Suitors of <hi>Cirenceſter,</hi> for that they did detain a man ſo long in priſon (that offered to acquit himſelfe) that he died there, as you may find, pag. 301. whereby you may clearly perceive, that the Liberties of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> as touching their perſons, are not grounded meerly upon <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> but are of a more ancient foundation, even in the originall Lawes of the Nation: the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> being onely a Declaration, or Confirmation of thoſe former Lawes which by Divine right, and Nature, we inherit. As Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in his Proeme to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of his Inſtitutes, obſerves, <hi>Theſe Lawes were gathered and obſerved amongst others in an intire volume by King</hi> EDWARD the
<hi>Confeſſor.</hi> And though that <hi>William the Conquerour</hi> came in by the Sword; yet at the petition of the Lords and Commons of this Realme, he confirmed theſe Lawes unto us for the ſake of King <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113893:5"/>
               <hi>Edward,</hi> that deviſed unto him the Kingdome; as witneſſe
<hi>Matth. Paris,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmeſbury,</hi> which were afterwards confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>King Henry the firſt,</hi> and enlarged by
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond in his <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> made at
<hi>Clarendon:</hi> and after much blood ſpent between King <hi>John</hi> and his <hi>Barons,</hi> concerning them; re-eſtabliſhed at <hi>Running Mead,</hi> neere <hi>Stanes:</hi> and laſtly, brought to a full growth, and made publique by King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in the ninth yeare of his reigne, though he ſought afterwards to avoid both that of his father King
<hi>John,</hi> upon pretence of dures of impriſonment, and his own by
<hi>nonage;</hi> Yet nevertheleſſe, God ſo ordaining, in the 20. year of his reigne he did confirm and compleat the ſaid <hi>Charter</hi> for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual eſtabliſhment of liberty to all <hi>free-born Engliſhmen,</hi> and their <hi>heirs</hi> for ever: ordaining, <hi>Quod contravenientes per Dominuns Regem, cum convicti fuerint, graviter puniantur.</hi> Which is, that thoſe that went againſt theſe lawes, when they were convicted; ſhould bee grievouſly puniſhed by our Lord the King. And in the 52. yeare of his reign by the <hi>Stat. of Marleb. c.</hi> 5. this Charter was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Act of Parliament: and hath ſince been not leſſe then 33. times confirmed and eſtabliſhed, and commanded to be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, by ſeverall Parliaments ſince held.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Charter</hi> of our Liberties, or Freemans
<hi>Birth-right,</hi> that coſt ſo much blood of our Anceſtors, and was ſo long in the Forge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it could be faſhioned: being no leſſe then
200. yeares under perſecution, before it was brought to perfection; is that brazen wall, and impregnable Bulwark that defends the Common liberty of
<hi>England</hi> from all illegall &amp; deſtructive <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, be it either by <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State</hi> endeavoured. And becauſe it imports us ſo much; we ſhall recite the words of this
<hi>Charter,</hi> as to our preſent purpoſe of the vindication of our liberties both of perſons &amp; eſtates. And firſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 14. it runs thus, <hi>A Freeman ſhall not be amerced for a ſmall fault; but after the manner of the fault: and for a great fault, after the greatneſſe thereof; ſaving to him his content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and a Merchant; ſaving to him likewiſe, his Merehandiſe. And none of the ſaid amercements ſhall be aſſeſſed but by oath of honeſt and lawful men of the vicinage.</hi> This part of the charter was made in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Common Law; as appeares by <hi>Glanvil, l. 9. c.</hi> 11. where he uſeth theſe words, <hi>Eſt autem miſerico dia domini Regis qua quio per juramentum legalium hominum de vicineto, eatenus amerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andus <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113893:6"/> eſt, ne quis de ſuo honorabili contenemento amittet.</hi> In <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus, The amercements, or mercy of the King, ought to be ſuch, whereby a man is to be amerced by the oath of lawfull men of the neighbourhood, or County, in ſuch manner, that he may not loſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of that countenance or ſubſiſtence, together with and by reaſon of his Free-hold: For ſo is the ſenſe of the word taken in the <hi>Statute of 1. Edw. 3. cap. 4. and vet. n. Br. fol.</hi> 11. The Armour and weapons, and profeſſion of a Souldier, is his countenance: And the books; of a Scholler. So Sir <hi>Edward Cook. 2. part of Inſtit. pag. 28. Amercements ought to be aſſeſſed by the equals of him that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merced.</hi> So is the expreſſe Book of 7.
<hi>H. 6. fo. 12. in Dett. Fitz. Herbert, Nat. Brev. fol.</hi> 73. And in caſe where a man is amerced; he ought not to be impriſoned: as appeares 11.
<hi>H. 4. fol.</hi> 55. The intent of which clauſe of the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> is, That no man ſhould be tried but by his Equals; as more fully appeares, <hi>cap.</hi> 29. where it is thus enacted, <hi>No Freeman ſhall be taken or impriſoned, or diſſeiſed of his Free-hold, or Liberties, or free Cuſtomes, or be out-lawed, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iled, or any otherwiſe deſtroyed: nor we will not paſſe upon him, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him, but by lawfull judgement of his PEERES, or by the law of the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe few words lies conched the liberty of the whole
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Nation.</hi> This word, <hi>liber Homo,</hi> or free Man, extends to all manner of <hi>Engliſh</hi> people; as appears <hi>Stamf. Pl. Coron. pag.</hi> 152. In theſe words of this Charter before recited, there are theſe 6. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>That no man ſhall be taken, or impriſoned, but by the law of the land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>That no man ſhall be diſſeiſed, diſpoſſeſſed,</hi> (ſequeſtred) <hi>or put out of his Free-hold:</hi> that is, lands or lively-hood, liberties, or free Cuſtomes; but by the Law of the Land.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>No man ſhall bee Out-lawed, but by the Law of the Land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, <hi>No man ſhall bee exiled, but according to the Law of the Land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fifthly, <hi>That no man ſhall be in any ſort deſtroyed, unleſſe it bee by the law of the land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sixthly, <hi>No man ſhall be condemned, but by a lawfull judgement of his Peeres, or by the law of the land.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113893:6"/> Where firſt it is to be noted, that theſe words, <hi>By lawfull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Peeres,</hi> or <hi>By the law of the land;</hi> are <hi>Synonyma's,</hi> or words of equall ſignification: and that the <hi>law of the land,</hi> and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>judgement of Peeres;</hi> are the <hi>proprium quarto modo,</hi> or eſſentiall qualities of this
<hi>Chapter</hi> of our <hi>great Charter,</hi> being communicable <hi>omni ſoli &amp; ſemper,</hi> to all and every clauſe thereof alike. Therefore we are to examine, declare, and publiſh to the world, what this <hi>Legale judicium,</hi> or <hi>Lexterrae,</hi> this lawfull judgement, or law of the land, is, and hath alwayes been taken to bee: That the <hi>Free-borne</hi> ſubjects of this Kingdome, may not dwell in the ſhade; but that they may be able to underſtand them with clearneſſe and perſpicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to demand them with force and vigour, as our Anceſtors in times of old, have in like caſe done; To make a cleare demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, we will follow the order of the ſix Particulars before mentioned, to be emergent out of this
<hi>Charter of our liberties.</hi> And firſt touching our caption and impriſonment, <hi>Nullus liber homo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatur aut impriſonetur, niſi per legale judicium Parium ſuorum, vel per legem terrae.</hi> Let no freeman of
<hi>England</hi> (which is every man born in the Realm) be taken or impriſoned, but by lawfull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Peeres, or the law of the land. This is the context of this clauſe: Every Arreſt, or Attachment, is compriſed within it. See <hi>Cook. 2. part. Inſtit. pag.</hi> 46. What the Law was before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Law; we have in part declared already: we ſhall onely adde this, That impriſonment without lawfull cauſe, was ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that among the lawes of King <hi>Alfred, cap.</hi> 31. wee find this,
<hi>Qui immerentem Pagaum vinculis conſtrinxerit decem ſolidis noxam ſarcito:</hi> If a man ſhould unjuſtly impriſon a Pagan, or a Heathen man; hee ſhould redeem his offence with the payment of ten ſhillings (no ſmall ſumme in thoſe dayes.) This is a perfect badge of liberty by our lawes. Let us now examine what it hath been ſince, by the <hi>Stat. of 25. E.
3. cap.</hi> 4.
<q rend="margQuotes">It is ordained, That none from henceforth ſhall bee taken by petition or ſuggeſtion made to our Lord the King, or to his Counſell: unleſſe it bee by Indictment, or Preſentment of his good and lawfull people of the ſame neighbourhood, where ſuch deeds, be done; in due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manner: By the <hi>Stat. of 25. E. 3. cap.</hi> 3. No man ſhall bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, without being brought to anſwer by due proceſſe of law. By the <hi>Stat. of 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. E. 3. c.</hi> 3. It is accorded for the good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113893:7"/> Governance of the Commons, That no man bee put to anſwer, without preſentment before Juſtices, or matter of Record, or by due Proceſſe, or Writ Originall, according to the old law of the land. And if any thing from henceforth be done contrary; it ſhall be void in law, and holden for error.</q>
            </p>
            <p>We need not cite the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> or other Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mentioned in our former Treatiſe <hi>for vindication of Liberty, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Slavery:</hi> Let us now examine the <hi>Reſponſa prudentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> upon theſe Statutes, and the Judgements given by thoſe Sages, 45. <hi>Aſſ. Plea. 5. Fitzherbert Title Aſſiſe, nu.</hi> 346. wee find that the Bayliffe of <hi>Chensford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> was indicted before <hi>Knevet</hi> and <hi>Thorp,</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> &amp; <hi>Terminer,</hi> for impriſoning a man, &amp; taking his goods by vertue of a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion out of
<hi>Chauncery,</hi> which he pleaded in his juſtification: The reſolution was,
<q rend="margQuotes">That the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and impriſonment were againſt law, to take a man &amp; his goods, without indictment, or ſuit of the party, or other due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of law. 33.
<hi>E. 3. Fitzh. title Treſpaſſe,</hi> 253. It is declared for Law, That the Command of the Lord is not a ſufficient warrant to one to take his villeine without due proceſſe of law. <hi>May 16. H. 6. Fitz. Monſtrans de faites, nu.</hi> 182. It is declared for Law, That if the King co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand a man to arreſt one, and the party doth it in his preſence; the arreſt is unlawfull, &amp; the party areſted may have his action of falſe impriſonment. 24. <hi>E. 3. fo. 9. Be. faux Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment.</hi> 9. You may find that a Commiſſion was directed to men to take divers notorious Felons before they were indicted, and this Commiſsion was adjudged void in Law.</q>
            </p>
            <p>We need not mention the reſolution of the Judges in this point of <hi>Liberty,</hi> you may find it reported by Sir <hi>E. Cook in his Reports, 9. Ja. f.</hi> 66. There are a thouſand caſes more cited in our books of law, to prove this undeniable truth: out of which we only cited theſe, to inform the free Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> That neither the King by his command or commiſsion, nor his Councell, nor the Lord of a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layne, can or could impriſon, arreſt, or attach any man without due proceſſe of law, or by legall judgement, and law of the land, againſt the forme of our defenſive <hi>Charter of Liberty,</hi> no not a <hi>Pagan or Heathen</hi> could be unjuſtly impriſoned or arreſted without due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Law. But to diſcourſe here the manifold impriſonments of the free-born people of this Kingdom, contrary to their <hi>Birth-right,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113893:7"/> this <hi>Free Charter,</hi> and contrary to the known lawes of this Realm: or to ſhew forth all the illegall proceſſe, whereby men are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes arreſted, attached, or impriſoned, contrary to this
<hi>Charter,</hi> and the lawes before recited: as <hi>Latitats, Capiats pro debito,</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments, and Meſſengers; would be infinite, and require a volume
<note place="margin">Which is worth the making.</note> by it ſelfe. Onely thus far we may be bold to demand, by what Law, Statute, or other legall power, the <hi>Committee of Examinations, Committees of Exciſe</hi> and
<hi>Sequeſtrations,;</hi> nay, all <hi>Committees:</hi> nay more, their
<hi>Sub Committees</hi> take upon them to commit to priſon: nay, without Baile or Mainpriſe, the free-born Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, without lawfull proceſſe, triall, or conviction, and moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly againſt the law of the land? For if thoſe whom we have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to ſit at the Helme of the government for us, as our <hi>Truſtees,</hi> for preſervation of our
<hi>Liberties,</hi> be (by right of their places) <hi>Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;</hi> we are ſure they cannot depute their <hi>Authorities.</hi> For a <hi>Judge cannot delegate his power to another, nor make a Deputy to judge for him;</hi> And this appeares by the Books of 2. <hi>H. 6. f. 37. 9. E. 4. f. 31. 41. 10. E. 4. f. 15. 11. E. 4. f.</hi> 1. I am ſure wee have not ſent them thither, and given them the places of their truſt to <hi>Them</hi> and their
<hi>Aſſignes:</hi> therefore their Committees, or Aſſignees, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not execute their Judiciall power: which as to the matter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, is one and the chiefeſt of their Judicial powers, ſo it bee according to due proceſſe of Law. But wee will not wrong theſe Noble Patriots, the
<hi>Commons of England,</hi> whom wee have choſen to be the Guardians of our Liberties; either to ſuſpect them not to be our competent Judges, and Judges of <hi>Record</hi> too, or that they intend to commit our liberties to their committing <hi>Commities;</hi> ſince that by deputing ſuch
<hi>Committes,</hi> and inveſting them with their own powers; it argues the givers rather to be Miniſteriall then Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall <hi>Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We come now to the ſecond particular, which is, <hi>That no man ſhall be deſſeiſed of his Free-hold, or Liberties, or free cuſtomes, but by lawfull judgement of his Peeres, or by the law of the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We need not inſiſt long upon this particular, it being ſo plain and cleare in it ſelfe; Onely wee will remember that which that learned Father in the Law, Sir <hi>Edward Cook. 2. part. Inſtit. pag</hi> 46. ſaith upon this clauſe, viz. <hi>Hereby is intended, that Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Goods and Chattels, ſhell not bee ſeized contrary to this great
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113893:8"/> Charter, and the Law of the Land. Nor any man ſhall bee diſſeiſed of his Lands or Tenements, or diſpoſſeſſed of his goods or chattels, contrary to to the law of the land.</hi> Wee may ſafely adde, That neither King nor State ought to ſeiſe, ſequeſter, plunder, or take away any mans goods, chattels, trade, lawfull calling or office; before the party be lawfully indicted or convicted of an offence by due proceſſe of Law, tryall of <hi>Jury,</hi> and lawfull <hi>Judgement,</hi> by the law of the land. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought any man to be diſſeiſed, or put out of his Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Freehold, by ſuggeſtion, or petition to the King, or his Councell, unleſſe it be by preſentment or indictment of his good and lawful people of the neighbourhood. That thisis as clear as the Sun at noon-day; Read theſe three Statutes of 5. <hi>E. 3. cap. 9. 25. E. 3. c. 4.
28. E. 3. c.</hi> 3. And the books of 43. <hi>Aſſ. Pl.</hi> 21. Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to ſequeſtring, ſeiſing, or deſſeiſing rather, of Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Free-hold of the free ſubjects of <hi>England.</hi> For the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our goods, not onely this great <hi>Charter,</hi> but alſo the Book of 43. <hi>E. 3. fo. 24. 32. 44. Aſſ. Pl. 14. 26. Aſſ. Pl. 32. 7. H. 4. fol. 47. Cook. 1. Reports. fol. 171. 8. Reports. fol. 125. Caſe of London:</hi> Where the caſe was, <hi>K. H. 6. granted to the Corporation of Dyers within London, power to ſearch, &amp;c.</hi> And if they found any cloath died with Logwood; that the cloath ſhould bee forfeit. And it was adjudged in <hi>Trin. 41. Eliz.</hi> in this caſe, That this Charter for ſeiſing of ſuch cloath, was againſt the Law of the land, and this great Charter; becauſe no man ought to have his goods taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him, before conviction. Nay, if he were accuſed or indicted of Felony or Treaſon; yet his goods ought not to bee ſeiſed upon, or taken away from him, before he be attainted or convicted, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> upon pain to forfeit the double va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue; as appeares by the Statute of 1. <hi>R.</hi> 3. And although Treaſon is not mentioned within that Statute, but Felony onely; yet Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cook. Inſtit. part. 3. fol.</hi> 228. ſaith, <hi>that Regularly the goods of any Delinquent cannot be taken and ſeiſed, before the ſame be forfeited. Neither is this a new opinion; but, the law ever was, and ſtill is ſo,</hi> as <hi>Bracton l. 3. fol.</hi> 136. witneſſeth in theſe words, <hi>Qui pro crimine, vel felonia magna, ſicut pro morte hominis captus fuerit, &amp; impriſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, vel ſub cuſtodia detentus; non debet ſpoliari bonis ſuis, nec de terris ſuis diſſeiſiri: ſed debet inde ſuſtentari donec de crimine ſibi impoſito ſe defenderit, vel convictus fuerit, quia ante convictionem nihil foriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facit.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113893:8"/> Et ſi quis contra hoc ſecerit, fiat Vic. tale brev. Rex Vic. ſalute, Scias quod proviſum eſt in Curia noſtra coram nobis, quod nullus homo captus pro morte hominis, vel alia felonia pro qua debeat impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonari, diſſeiſeatur de terris, tenementis, vel catallis ſuis, quouſque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victus fuerit de felonia de qua indictus eſt, &amp;c.</hi> In
<hi>Engliſh</hi> thus, Where any man for a crime, or great felony, as, for murder; ſhall be taken and impriſoned, or detained under cuſtody, he ought not to be ſpoyled of his goods, nor diſſeiſed of his lands; but ought to be maintained of the ſame, untill he ſhall acquit himſelfe of the crime charged upon him, or ſhall be convicted thereof, becauſe,
<hi>Before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction he ſhall forfeit nothing.</hi> And if any man ſhall doe contrary to this courſe; let there be made out to the Sheriffe, ſuch a Writ fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>THE KING to the Sheriffe, greeting, Know thou, that it is provided in our Court before us, that no man taken for the death of a man, or other felony, for which he ought to bee impriſoned; ought to be diſſeiſed of his Lands, Tenements, or Chattels, until he ſhal be convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of the Felony, whereof hee is indicted, &amp;c.</hi> In which words,
<hi>Qui pro crimine,</hi> Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> is of opinion, that Treaſon is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as alſo, <hi>Quia ante convictionem.</hi> And that the Act of
<hi>Magna Charta, c.</hi> 29. extends to treaſon as well as to Felony, or other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency. The Writ aforementioned, you may find in the
<hi>Regiſter</hi> among the Originall Writs. By all which Statutes and Book-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and a thouſand more teſtimonies to be produced; it is more then cleare, That neither, Sequeſtration, Seiſure, nor taking or ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a man of his lands, or goods; ought to be: till hee bee lawfully indicted and convicted by triall of his equals, according to the law of the land.</p>
            <p>But we have done with this particular: wee come now to the next, which is the third, and that is, <hi>No man ought to bee out-lawed, by the Law of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word <hi>Outlary</hi> ſignifieth, The putting of a man out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Law, either in Criminall or Civill cauſes; and it is of two kindes, <hi>Legall</hi> and <hi>Illegall.</hi> A legall outlary is, when the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is duly indicted, or ſummoned to appear and makes default at the return of the Writ of Summons, and then by due proceſſe of Law is pronounced an <hi>Outlaw</hi> in the County-Court, by the Coroners of the County where he doth inhabit. Which proceeding is according to the law of the land, becauſe it is done by his <hi>Equals.</hi> And if he <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113893:9"/> be duly out-lawed of Treaſon, Murder, or Felony; it is a conviction in law till he appear, &amp; plead to the indictment, and pray his Writ of error, to reverſe the outlary: which ought to be allowed him upon his appearance. <hi>Illegall Outlaries</hi> in Civil Cauſes, are, where men are not duly ſummoned, and a falſe Returne made by the Sheriffe: whereby proceſſe of Law is unduly awarded againſt him, till he be outlawed. In both which caſes he forfeits his goods and chattels, and the profits of his lands, till the outlary bee reverſed. There are other ſorts of illegall outlaries in effect; which are, putting men out of protection of the law: which are unlawfull prohibitions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions: whereby men are enjoyned and ſtayed from proſecuting their rights, ſuits, or actions in any of his Majeſties Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: Or, when men under any pretence of incapacity by delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency, are not permitted to ſue, or have right denied them by any Judges or Juſtices; theſe are in effect outlaries: <hi>For every Outlary carries with it an incapacity to ſue for a mans right</hi> or for wrong done in any perſonal or mixt action. <hi>As Littleton in his chapter of Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,</hi> affirmes; and as you may find 2. &amp; 3 <hi>Ph. &amp; Mar. Dier.</hi> 114. 115. Now it is all one to be put out of protection of the law, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not to be permitted to ſue for a mans right, or to bee ſtaied by injunction or pronibition, ſo that a man cannot proceed. All which cauſes are illegall, and contrary to this clauſe of the great Charter: <hi>For every man ought to bee permitted to goe to triall, judgement, and execution in his cauſe, according to the courſe of the law of the land.</hi> And if he faile in his ſuit, he ſhall pay coſts, and be amerced, <hi>pro fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo clamore.</hi> Which amencement ought to bee reaſonable, <hi>&amp; ſalvo contenemento,</hi> that he be not
<hi>deſtroyed,</hi> as is before declared. Which payment of deſtruction, is the fourth particular, and now comes to be handled. The words of the great Charter, are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That no man ſhall be any way deſtroyed, but by judgement of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, or according to the law of the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word <hi>deſtruere</hi> amongſt the Grammarians,
<hi>eſt idem quod pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus evertere &amp; diruere,</hi> to deſtroy is all one, as <hi>utterly to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw</hi> and <hi>demoliſh:</hi> To deſtroy a man is to <hi>forejudge a man of life, limb, or liberty, to diſ-herit, to put to torture or death, any man without lawfull tryall, due preparation to his defence, or by SURREPTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIOUS IUDGEMENT.</hi> All which are contrary to the law of the land. It is the <hi>Genus</hi> of all the former particulars, it is the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113893:9"/> moſt pernicious extent of all arbitrary power, there have been to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples of it, <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> in the 14. <hi>E.</hi> 2. was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; that is, <hi>adjudged to dye as a Traytor without lawfull try all of his Peers.</hi> And afterwards,
<hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> his brother was reſtored:</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe that he was not arraigned and put to anſwer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe, that contrary to this Charter of Liberties, the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> being one of the Peers of the Realm; without anſwer, or lawfull judgment of his Peers he was put to death: Such like proceedings were had in the caſe of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> as appears <hi>P. 39. Coram Rege,</hi> and in the E. of <hi>Aruudels</hi> caſe
<hi>Rot. Par. 4. E. 3. Nu.</hi> 13. and in Sir <hi>John Alees</hi> caſe, 4.
<hi>E. 3. Nu.</hi> 2. Such was the deſtruction com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon the Lord
<hi>Haſtings</hi> in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>K. Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> the 3. who ſware he would not dye, before he ſaw his head off; and thereupon cauſed him to be executed without tryall, anſwer, or lawfull conviction: ſuch was the deſtruction of the Lord <hi>Rivers,</hi> and many other of ſad remembrance: but above all that Attainder of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cromwell</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſen,</hi> who was attainted of high Treaſon, as appears, <hi>Rot. Part. 32. H.</hi> 8. being committed to the Tower of
<hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and forth-coming to be heard, and yet never called to anſwer in any of the Houſes of Parliament, they ſitting: which we hope ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be more drawn into preſident, but wiſh with a clearned ſage in the Law, <hi>Quod auferat oblivio ſi poteſt, ſi non, utcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſilentium tegat,</hi> which is; let oblivion take away the memory of ſo foul a fact, if it can: if it cannot, let ſilence cover it: For, the more high and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Court is, the more juſt and honourable it ought to be in the proceeding, and to give example of Juſtice to inferiour Courts; for theſe <hi>deſtructores ſubditorum dom. Regis,</hi> the deſtroyers of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born people of the Kingdom, were ever-odious and hatefull to the ſubject, and ſevere pains appointed for them, as appears by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of
<hi>Kenelworth, Par.</hi> 16. and by the old Statute of <hi>Rag-man;</hi> and that this kind of deſtroying the Kings people, is utterly againſt the Law of the Land, is moſt evident; not only by the great Charter, but alſo by the Statute of 5. c. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. and 28. <hi>E. 3. c.</hi> 3. afore-mentioned, and by the ancient Lawes of the Land; as appears by
<hi>Horn,</hi> in his <hi>Mirrour of Juſtice, c, 2. ſect.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>We proceed now to <hi>Exile,</hi> which is the fifth particular: The great <hi>Charter</hi> runs thus; <hi>No man ſhall be exiled, but by the Law of the Land.</hi> 
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113893:10"/> Exile or baniſhment is of two ſorts: The one, a voluntary, which is at the Common-Law; and that is, when a man would abjure the Realm for a Fellony committed by him, having taken ſanctuary to avoid the puniſhment of death, chuſing rather perpetuall baniſhment then to put himſelf to the hazard of his life, by a legall tryall for his offence, as <hi>Stamf. Pl. Cor. p.</hi> 117.</p>
            <p>The other is, when a man is inforced to baniſhment, which is only legally done by Act of Parliament; as appeares by the Statute of
<hi>Weſtrn. 1. cap. 20, 35. El. c.</hi> 1. and 39. <hi>El. c.</hi> 4. and by that Judgment or Statute of baniſhment made of the two <hi>Spencers, 15. E.</hi> 2. called <hi>Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Hugonis le-Deſpencer, patris &amp; filii:</hi> for, though there was an Order or Ordinance made in the Lords houſe, <hi>Anno
6. E. 3. Nu.</hi> 6. That ſuch learned men in the Law, as ſhould be ſent as Juſtices, or otherwiſe, to ſerue in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould have no excuſe: yet ſaith Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke, 2. part. Inſtit. p.</hi> 48. That Order or Ordinance being no Act of Parliament, it did not bind the ſubject; ſo that we that are the free-born ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> cannot at this day be enforced or compelled to depart the Realme, or be exiled or baniſhed from our native Country, but by Act of Parliament;</p>
            <p>And from this, we paſſe to examine what is to be eſteemed a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Judgment of our Peers, and what is here in this <hi>Charter,</hi> meant by the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Great Charter</hi> was penned in Latine; the words are thus: <hi>Nec ſuper eum ibimus, nec ſuper eummittemus, niſi per legale judicium Parium ſuorum,</hi> which are more emphatically in the Latine, then in our Engliſh Tranſlations of this <hi>Charter:</hi> for the Tranſlations render it,
<q rend="margQuotes">We will not paſſe upon, nor condemn any man, but by the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full judgment of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land:</q> whereas the words in the Latine import,
<q rend="margQuotes">That the King ſhall not in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when he is perſonally preſent in his high Court of Parliament, or any other of his Courts of Juſtice; cauſe any man to be otherwiſe tryed or condemned, then by lawfull judgment of his Peers, or the law of the Land,</q> 
               <hi>nec ſuper eum mittemus,</hi> that is,
<q rend="margQuotes">That no Judges, Commiſſioners, or Juſtices of the King, ſhall by force of any Writ, or Commiſſion from the King, under the Great Seal, in his abſence, arraign, try, or condemn any man, but by the lawfull judgment of his Peers, or by the law of the Land.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now this <hi>legale judicium parium ſuorum,</hi> or lawfull judgment of <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113893:10"/> a mans Peers, is, and hath alwayes had a two-fold conſtruction in law; the one is, <hi>When a Lord of the Parliament hath committed trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or felony, or other capitall offence, whereby he is indictable at the Kings Suite; there he by vertue of this Charter ought to be tryed by his Peers,</hi> that is, ſuch as are Lords of Parliament, that ſit there, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Nobility: for no Noble-man that is not a Lord of the Parliament, or any other that ſits in the Lords houſe by Writ, <hi>Et non ratione nobiliatis;</hi> can be a tryer of a Lord of the Parliament, or chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge this priviledge of tryall in caſe of Treaſon, Fellony, or other capitall offence: But a Noble-man of the Parliament ſhall not have this priviledge, either upon an Indictment of <hi>Praemunire,</hi> or upon an Appeale of Fellony, at the ſuit of the party, or in any Civill-Action, either concerning the right of Lands, or of other Poſſeſſions, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſonall Action, brought by a Common-perſon, againſt a Lord of the Parliament, as appeares unto us by the Bookes of 1. <hi>H. 4. f. 1 13. H. 8. f.
12. 10. E. 4. fol.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>This tryall of Noble-men by their Peers at the Kings Suit; is not upon Oath as in the caſe of common perſons: for the Peers are not ſworn before the Lord Steward, before whom this tryall muſt bee had: but they are to be charged by the Lord Steward, <hi>ſuper fidelita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus &amp; ligeantiis Dom. Regi debitis;</hi> that is, upon their faith and allegeance due to the King; and if they acquit the Peer or Noble-man, upon whom they paſſe; the Entry is, <hi>Willelmus Comes E. &amp; cateri Antedicti pares inst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nter ſuper fidelitatibus &amp; ligeantiis dicto D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. Regi debitis per praefaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seneſcallu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab inferiori uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad ſupremum ſeparatim examinati; dicunt, quod Wil. Dom. Dacre nox eſt Culp.</hi> and ſo was the Entry in the caſe of the Lord <hi>Dacres 26. H.
8. Spilmans</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and Cookes <hi>Inſtit. 3. part. p.</hi> 30. If a Noble-man be indicted of Treaſon, Felony, or Murder, and cannot be found; he ſhall be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed by the Coroners of the County: and in caſe of Clergy, no Noble-man ſhall have more priviledge then a common-perſon, where it is not ſpecially provided for them by Act of Parliament; as by <hi>Stamford pl. Cor. p.</hi> 130. is made manifeſt: out of all which, we gather, that a Nobleman hath this priviledge of tryal, as well <hi>per lege terra,</hi> as by this Charter: and that anciently, <hi>legale judicium parium,</hi> or lawfull tryall of Peers, for all manner of perſons, aſwell Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as Commons: was,
<hi>vere-dictum duodecim proborum &amp; legalium hominum de vicineto,</hi> a verdict of 12. good and lawfull men of the <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113893:11"/> Neighbour-hood; that is, of the Commons of England, &amp; ſo ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſaving only in this excepted caſe, by the Great Charter, which ſhewes, that there can be no <hi>legale judicium,</hi> or lawfull judgment; but it muſt be <hi>per legem terrae,</hi> or according to the Law of the Land, which is the other branch of this judgment, as to the Commons of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to prove that <hi>legale judicium parium,</hi> or lawfull judgment of a mans Peers or Equals, is by verdict of 12. men, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for the word <hi>Peers</hi> vinvocally ſignifies both. Let us conſult both the judgment of Parliaments in this point, and the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lawes of the Land:</p>
            <p>And firſt, for the opinions of Parliaments in this point, we finde, that by the ſtatute of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.
<q rend="margQuotes">None ſhall be taken by petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſuggeſtion, made to our Lord the King, or to his Councell; unleſſe it be by indictment or preſentment, of his good and lawfull people of the ſame neighbour-hood 42. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. It is aſſented, and accorded, for the good governance of the Commons, that no man be put to anſwer without preſentment before Juſtices, or matter of Record, or by due proceſſe and Writ, originall, according to the old law of the Land; and if any thing be done fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it ſhall be void in law, and holden for errour;</q> and to ſay one word for all: there are above 50 ſtatutes now in print, and in force, that warrant this tryall, or <hi>legale judicium parium ſuorum,</hi> or tryall by a mans Equals or Peers, made ſince the Great Charter in ſeverall caſes: the citing of which ſtatutes; for prolixity we avoid: And that this manner of tryall was the old law of the Land, wee are here to make it appear; that this manner of tryall, is according to the law of the Land, and that there is none other: wherein we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this diſtinction, that this <hi>legale judicium,</hi> or lawfull judgment, is two-fold: The one is of the matter of Fact: The other is of matter of Law; That which is of matter of Fact, is to be tryed, <hi>per lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le indicium parium,</hi> or a lawfull tryall of a mans Peers: That which is of matter of Law, is to be tryed by the Judges, or Juſtices of the Land, authorized thereunto by the Kings lawfull Commiſſions: To prove, that there is no other lawfull Judgment of our Peeres or Equals,</p>
            <p>As touchiug the matter of Fact, we are to examine the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Common-wealth, and the originall conſtitutions thereof:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113893:11"/> We find that King <hi>Alfred</hi> having reduced this Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into an Entire-Monarchy divided it into 38. Counties, and each County into ſeverall Hundred and Mannors: The Counties were put under the government of Earles, who ſubſtituted under them Viſcounts or Sheriffes, for the quiet government of the people, the Hundreds and Mannors ſubordinately under the ſeverall Lords of them.</p>
            <p>The Sheriffes had two Courts; to wit, the Sheriffes-Tourn, and the County-Court: The firſt, for offences againſt the peace of the Land: The latter, for entry and determination of civill-cauſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween party and party.</p>
            <p>In the firſt indictment, or preſentment of offences was made
<hi>per-Enqueſt;</hi> that is, by Juries.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond, the <hi>Free-ſuiters;</hi> that is, men of the neighbor-hood. The like was done in the <hi>leets</hi> or <hi>viewes</hi> of
<hi>Frankepledge,</hi> and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred-Courts</hi> in the <hi>Hundreds.</hi> The like proceedings was in the <hi>Leets,</hi> and <hi>Court-Barons of Mannors</hi> in thoſe Courts. There was no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation or judgment given, but by the Enquirie of good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men of the neighbor-hood.</p>
            <p>This every book of the Law tells us; for more particular ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, read <hi>Horn, f.</hi> 8. and fore-ward. Theſe Courts were formed after the modell of the greater Courts of the Realme, the
<hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and <hi>Common-pleas,</hi> where greater juriſdiction was, as to the matter to be enquired of; but no variation originally in the manner of proceeding; only the juriſdiction of the Court of
<hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> in tryals of actions, <hi>ad dampnum</hi> 40. s. flowed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the whole Kingdome. The other Courts were confined to their ſeverall limits, and might not exceed 40. s. damages:
<hi>theſe were the originall Courts of the Kingdome:</hi> and the <hi>legale judicium parium,</hi> or lawfull judgment of Peers, was only tryall by Jury of Equals, before this great Charter: From which tryals, this clauſe is inſerted into it, and by an inviolable right of law continues in force, even to this day, as every free ſubject of <hi>England</hi> by experience knowes; and as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry book of our law proves into us, <hi>the verdict of the Jury in criminall cauſes, being the judgment of Attainder,</hi> and in civill cauſes a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as <hi>Stamford, pl. Cor. p</hi> 44. and ali other bookes prove; And to leave every man without ſcruple in this particular; we finde by the ſtatute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> the 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12. That in caſe of Felony, thoſe that refuſe <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113893:12"/> upon their arraignment, to put themſelves upon the Enqueſt, ſhall be put to pennance
<hi>fort, &amp; dure,</hi> which is, ſtoned or preſſed to death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they refuſe as the ſtatute ſaith, to ſtand <hi>to the Law of the Land,</hi> And yet if the party accuſed ſtand mute, and will not put himſelfe upon the Enqueſt; the Judge ought to examine the evidence, and to enquire by the Iury, whether he were mute of malice, or by the Act of God, before he ſhall give judgment againſt the Priſoner: <hi>ſo tender is the Law of the Land of the life of every man,</hi> that if an Offendor would wilfully caſt away his life by contumacy; yet he ought not to be condemned; but <hi>per legale judicium parium ſuorum,</hi> or lawfull verdict of a Jury, which is according to the Law of the Land: this appeares by <hi>Stamf. pl. Cor. p. 150. a, b, c, d. Cookes Inſtit. p.</hi> 2. <hi>part. page</hi> 178. and ſo from this <hi>legale judicium parium,</hi> or lawfull judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Peers or Equals; we come to declare to the free-born ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>England,</hi> what this <hi>lex-terrae,</hi> or Law of the Land is.</p>
            <p>And firſt, we ſay, that this <hi>lex terrae,</hi> or law of the Land is <hi>the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute perfection of reaſon;</hi> as Sir <hi>Edw. Cook.</hi> 2. <hi>part, Inſtit. page</hi> 179. ſaith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is the law of <hi>England;</hi> and therefore all Commiſſions made to the Judges of the Land, run thus; That they in all caſes that come before them, <hi>facturi ſunt inde quod adjuſtitiam pertinet ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Angliae,</hi> the Judges by their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to judge and act only that which to iuſtice belongs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law of the land, and cuſtome of <hi>England,</hi> as. 2, <hi>part of Cooks Inſtit. p.</hi> 51. and dayly experience tells us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>it conſiſts of the lawfull and reaſonable uſages and cuſtoms received, and time-out-of-mind obſerved and approved by the people of this Kingdome:</hi> for if a cuſtome or uſage be not lawfull, it ought not to bind; <hi>Quod ab initio vitioſum eſt; non poteſt tractu tempor is conva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Vlpian, l.</hi> 29. Courſe of time amends not that which was naught from the firſt beginning, and in <hi>Jur. Reg. v.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 117 <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>non firmatur tractu tempora, quod de jure ab initio non ſubſiſtat,</hi> That which was not grounded upon good right, is not made good by continuance of time, and they muſt be reaſonable too: ſo is <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> opinion, in his Book <hi>de vera Religione, cap.</hi> 31. <hi>mihilex eſſenon videtur que Juſta noneſt;</hi> It ſeemes (ſaith he to me) to be no law at all, which is not juſt: It muſt likewiſe be received, and approved by the people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113893:12"/> Therefore, <hi>Ulpian F. de leg.</hi> 32.
<hi>Leges nulla alia cauſa nos tenent quam quod judicio populi receptae ſunt;</hi> the lawes doe therefore bind the Subject, becauſe they are received by the judgment of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and <hi>Gratian in Dec. diſtinct.</hi> 4. <hi>Thum demum humane leges ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent vim ſuam cum fuerint non modo inſtitutae, ſed etiam firmatae appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batione Comunitatis;</hi> It is then, that humane Laws have their ſtrength when they ſhall not only be deviſed, but by the approbation of the people; confirmed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this law of the land conſiſts of the antient Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and moderne Acts of Parliament, made by the Eſtates of the Realme; but of theſe only, ſuch as are agreeable to the Word of God, and law of Nature: for, as <hi>Gregory de valentia, Ex Tho. q.</hi> 93.
<hi>art.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; q.</hi> 94. <hi>art.</hi> 34. well obſerves, Humane law is a righteous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, agreeing with the Law naturall and eternall; and <hi>Auguſtine de libero Arbitrio, cap.</hi> 36. <hi>nihil juſtum eſt at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> legitimum, quod non ab aeterna lege ſibi homines derivaverint:</hi> there is nothing juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which men have not derived unto themſelves from the law eternall; And <hi>Horn, cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ſect.</hi>
1. ſaith,
<q rend="margQuotes">That torvous uſages, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt decrees not warrantable by Law, nor ſufferable by holy Scripture; are not to be uſed or obeyed: Out of all which premiſes, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the Law of the Land, is the Law of <hi>England;</hi> the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reaſon conſiſting of lawfull and reaſonable Cuſtomes, received and approved by the people, and of the old Conſtitutions and modern Acts of Parliament, made by the Eſtates of the Realme, and ſuch only as are agreeable both to the law eternall and naturall; and not contrary, but warrantable by the Word of God, whatſoever laws uſages, or cuſtomes, are not thus quallified, are not the law of the land, nor are to be obſerved or obeyed by the people, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Birth-right, and the freedome and liberty which by the law of God, the lawes of the Land, and this great Charter they ought to enjoy.</q> The ſumme of all is, that according to this Charter, the ſtatute and lawes afore-mentioned, no man ought to be taken or impriſoned or diſſeized of his free-hold, liberties, or free-cuſtomes: or out-lawed, or baniſhed, or my manner of way deſtroyed, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,
<q rend="margQuotes">but by lawfull tryal of his Peers or Equals, or by the law of the Land; that is, by due proceſſe of Law, by preſentment or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment of good and lawful men, where ſuch deeds he done in due manner, or by Writ originall at the Common-law, according
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113893:13"/> to the old law of the Land.</q> Here we will anſwer an objection, that we heare is made, which is, that this is an old Law, and many lawes have been made againſt it ſince it was granted, which weaken the ſtrength of this Charter.</p>
            <p>To this we anſwer, That by the Statutes of 28. <hi>E.</hi> 1. called <hi>Articuli. ſuper Cartas.</hi> &amp; 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>vet Magna Charta, fol.</hi> 137. and 37. called <hi>confirmatio Chartarum;</hi> It is provided,
<q rend="margQuotes">That if any judgment be given againſt any points of this great Charter, or the Charter of the Forreſt by any Iuſtices of the King, or other his Miniſters, it ſhall be undone and holden for nought, and by the ſtatute of 42. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. all Statutes made againſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> are repealed.</q> True it is, we find that 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3. by the practiſes of
<hi>Empſon,</hi> and <hi>Dudley;</hi> there was a ſtatute made in the face of this great Charter, whereby many exactions and oppreſſions were put in practice upon the free ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> to their great trouble and vexation: but
<note place="margin">Oh! for the like juſtice now, and if it were not? what would become of all our Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Judges, monopolizing Pattentee, Merchants, and arbitrary Committee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> we find withall, that they were hanged that put it in execution, and in the 1. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 6. That illegal Statute of 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. was repealed, and made void, and the cauſe ſpecified to be, becauſe it was againſt this Great Charter, and the law of the Land, but to put all out of doubt.
<q rend="margQuotes">Theſe clauſes of the Great Charter, which we have diſcourſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hitherto,</q> are all confirmed by the
<hi>Petition of Right,</hi> in the 3. year of this King.</p>
            <p>Now for remedy againſt any man that will infringe this Charter to the injury of any free-man that ought to have benefit of it; the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty grieved may have an Action vpon the great Charter againſt the party offending, as was brought againſt the <hi>Prior of Oſwin, P.</hi> 2.
<hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 538. <hi>in Banco Regis;</hi> and we find in the Regiſter-Book of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <hi>fol.</hi> 64. a Writ directed to the Sheriffe, <hi>Adcapiend: impugnato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Juris Regis &amp; ad ducendum cos, ad Gaolam de Newgate,</hi> to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the oppoſers of the Kings Charter, and to bring them to the Goal of Newgate: or the party grieved may indict the Offendor at the Kings Suit, for going <hi>contra formam Magnae Chartae,</hi> whereof we find a Preſident in <hi>Sheffields caſe, Paſch.</hi> 3.
<hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>B. R.</hi> Or the party grieved may bring his Writ, <hi>de Odio &amp; Aſtutia, de homine Replegian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, or Habeas Corpus,</hi> as appeares by the Regiſter, <hi>f.</hi> 77. and by the Statute of
<hi>Weſim.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 29. and by the Statute of <hi>Glouc. c.</hi>
9. as his caſe ſhall require.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſſected the ſeverall branches of this Great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113893:13"/> which moſt eminently concern our publike liberty, the birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of the free born ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> and ſtated the queſtion thereof. We will now with all due regard to the houſe of Peers, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine that judgment or ſentece pronounced againſt that impregnable Bulwark of the common-liberty, Lieutenant Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and the proceedings leading thereunto, by the Rules of this lawful judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or law of the land, mentioned in the great Charter (profeſſing, that as we will be tender, not willing to derogate at all from any lawful power, juriſdiction, or priviledge of that honourable houſe; ſo we will be as careful in preſerving and maintaining our liberties) ſwerving neither on the one ſide, nor on the other, from the true nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of the fact, nor the literal declaration of the order, &amp; ſentence, as it hath been repreſented unto us.</p>
            <p>And firſt we ſhal ſhew, out of what fountain; all the troubles of this worthy Gentleman have ſprung, (which is no other then from his fidelity, and love to his Country) they have been all occaſioned by his proſecution of Col. <hi>Edw. King,</hi> upon certain Articles exhibited againſt this Colonel, to the honourable houſe of Commons, in <hi>Aug.</hi>
1644. which yet hang there undetermined, and which charge the ſaid Colonel with diſloyalty infidelity, treachery, and breach of truſt to the Parliament, to whom he was a ſworn ſervant, and entertained in their pay. To prevent this Gentlemans proſecution; Col. <hi>King</hi> did by undue meanes cauſe him to bee impriſoned, <hi>July</hi> 19. 1645. where being removed to Newgate, he remained till the 14. of <hi>March</hi> 1645. upon which day, upon Mr. Recorders motion in the houſe of Commons, hee was enlarged, there, being nothing objected againſt him, and was by Col. <hi>King</hi> afterwards cauſed to be arreſted, <hi>April</hi> 14. 1646. as he was going to proſecute and purſue this Colonell for the Publike good, and for matters contained in thoſe Articles, and to follow his other buſineſſe, depending in Parliament: For, <hi>Intereſt Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publice, ut puniantur rei, ne per omiſſionem unius, multi atrociora per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrent ſlagitia,</hi> as
<hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>It is profitable for the Common-wealth, that guilty perſons bee puniſhed, leaſt by omiſſion of the puniſhment of one; many men by that ill example may be encouraged to commit more heinous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>This Arreſt was illegal, and a breach of priviledge of Parliament to the houſe of Commons, who were originally poſſeſſed, of the <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113893:14"/> Cauſe: for, all ſuitors in any Court of Juſtice at <hi>Weſtrn.</hi> ought to have the protection and priviledge of that Court, where they ſue againſt any that ſhall arreſt them in any other Court for the ſame matters, <hi>Eundo, morando, &amp; rediendo,</hi> which is, going thither, ſtaying there, &amp; returning homeward from their proſecution; as by 27. <hi>H</hi> 6. <hi>Fitzh. pr.</hi> 4. and divers other Bookes appears; and being put to plead by this unjuſt provocation to that action, he wrote that letter or booke to Mr. <hi>Juſtice Reeve,</hi> the 6. of <hi>June,</hi> 1646. whereat the great offence is taken, and upon which his grand charge was grounded, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding was very quick; for the 10. of Iune there was a Warrant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Gentleman-Uſher attending the Lords houſe, or his Deputy, from the Lords, to ſummon him to appeare before their Lordſhips: the next day being the 11. he was ſummoned, and the ſame day he appeared before the Lords Bar; and being brought to the Bar, was asked, whether he wrote that letter or booke to Iuſtice <hi>Reeve:</hi> (here is an examination, <hi>ore tenus,</hi> not uſual in Parliament, but frequent in Star-Chamber,) and being earneſtly preſt in it; the ſame 11. day of Iune; he delivered in a paper, containing his plea and defence; whereupon the ſame day he was committed by their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips priſoner to Newgate, for delivering in his plea and defence, which they in their Warrant call a ſcandalous and contemptuous paper,
<q rend="margQuotes">being in truth but a recital and declaration of the Lawes &amp; Statutes of <hi>England</hi> that made for his defence, and a declaratory of the liberties of all the Commons of
<hi>England,</hi> which by law they ought to enjoy, and by nature is their proper and free birth-right;</q> and the 16. of the ſame moneth he preſented his Petition to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable houſe of Commons, againſt their Lordſhips proceedings,
<q rend="margQuotes">being in the nature of an Appeale to the Commons; as his proper and onely Iudges.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The 22. of <hi>June,</hi> the Lords ſent an Order to the Keeper of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,
<q rend="margQuotes">to bring Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> againe to their Bar the next day; &amp; becauſe he refuſed to kneel at their Barre, was the next day being the 23. of <hi>June</hi> committed cloſe priſoner to Newgate, and not permitted to have Pen, Ink, or Paper, and none to have acceſſe to him in any kind but only his Keeper, untill that Court ſhould take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Where he remained in this condition till the Tenth day of Iuly,
1646. which day, Serjeant <hi>Nathaniel Finch</hi> delivered into the ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113893:14"/> houſe of Lords, certain Articles, with certain Bookes and Papers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed againſt the ſaid Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>JOHN LILBVRN:</hi> which you have word for word here printed. <hi>July</hi> the tenth, 1646. The Charge againſt Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>JOHN LILBVRN,</hi> as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="articles">
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113893:15"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>ARTICLES,</hi> Exhibited before the Lords in Parlia-ment aſſembled, by <hi>Nathanael Finch,</hi> Knight, and one of his
<hi>Majeſties Ser-geants at Law,</hi> againſt Lieu. Colonell <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> for high Crimes and Miſdemeanors done and committed by him.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="article">
                           <head>I.</head>
                           <p> VVHereas rhe Right Honorable, <hi>Edward,</hi> Earle of
<hi>Mancheſter,</hi> by the ſpace of divers yeares laſt paſt, hath been, and yet is, one of the Peeres of this Realm: And where as the ſaid Earle was, by Ordinance of Parliament, appointed Generall of divers Forces rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Parliament; the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburne,</hi> intending to ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize and diſhonour the ſaid Earle, and to raiſe diſcord between the ſaid Earle, and other the ſubjects of this Realm: He, the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburne,</hi> in a certain Book hereunto annexed, and by him contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and cauſed to be printed and publiſhed, intituled, <hi>The juſt Mans juſtification:</hi> Or, <hi>A Lettnr by way of Plea in Bar;</hi> hath falſly and ſcandalouſly, in certain Paſſages of the ſaid Book, affirmed and publiſhed, concerning the ſaid Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and his <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113893:15"/> demeanour in his ſaid Office and Imployment: And touching the complaint by the ſaid <hi>Lilburn</hi> alledged to be made by him, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the ſaid Earle, relating to the ſaid Earle, as followeth, <hi>Pa. 2. I complained to the Earle of Mancheſter thereof, being both his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and mine. And at the ſame time divers Gentlemen of the Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mittee of Lincoln,</hi> as Mr, <hi>Archer, &amp;c.</hi> having Articles of a very high nature againſt him; preſſed my Lord (meaning the ſaid Earl) to a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of him at a Councell of warre: And at the very ſame time, the Major, Aldermen, and Town-Clerk of <hi>Boſton,</hi> came to <hi>Lincoln</hi> to my Lord (meaning the ſaid Earle) with Articles of a ſuperlative na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt <hi>King their Governor;</hi> but could not get my Lord (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſaid Earle) to let us enjoy juſtice at a Councel of War, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all our expectations, &amp; as of right we ought to have had; which at preſent ſaved his head upon his ſhoulders. And page 8. and 9. of that Book did affirm theſe words, <hi>viz, We could not at all prevaile: the reaſon of which I am not able to render; unleſſe it were, that his two Chaplaines, Lee and Garter, prevailed with the Earle,</hi> (meaning the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Mancheſters two Chaplains, Aſh and Goode, to caſt a Clergie-miſt over their Lords</hi> (meaning the ſaid Earles) <hi>eyes,</hi> that he ſhould not bee able to ſee any deformity in Colonell <hi>King.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="article">
                           <head>II.</head>
                           <p>THe ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilbure</hi> within three moneths laſt paſt, in a certaine book by him contrived, and cauſed to be printed and publiſhed hereunto annexed, intituled, <hi>The Free-mans Freedom vindicated:</hi> or, <hi>A true Relation of the cauſe and manner of Lieu. Colonell Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burns preſent impriſonment in Newgate, being thereunto arbitrarily and illegally committed by the Houſe of Peeres,</hi> June 11.
1646. <hi>for his delivering in at their open Barre under his hand and ſeal, his Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt their incroaching upon the common liberties of all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England, in endeavouring to try him, a Commoner of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in a criminall cauſe, contrary to the expreſſe tenor and form of the 29 chapter of the great Charter of England.</hi> And for making his legall and juſt appeale to his competent, proper, and legall Tryers, and Judges, the Commons of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament aſſembled; did falſly and ſcandalouſly, in the eighth page of that Book, publiſh and affirm concerning the ſaid Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> theſe falſe and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113893:16"/> words: <hi>I clearly perceive the hand of</hi> Ioab <hi>to be in this, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, my old back-friend the Earle of Mancheſter; the fountain (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) of all my preſent troubles; who would have hanged me for taking a Caſtle from the Cavaliers in Yorkeſhire;</hi> but is ſo cloſely glu'd in in intereſt to that party, that hee protected from juſtice, Colonel <hi>King,</hi> one of his own Officers, for his good ſervice in treacherouſly delivering or betraying
<hi>Crowland</hi> to the Cavaliers, and never called, nor (that I could heare) deſired to call to account his Officer, or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, that baſely, cowardly, and treacherouſly betrayed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Lincoln</hi> laſt up to the enemy, without ſtriking one ſtroke, or ſtaying till ſo much as a Troop of Horſe, or a Trumpetter came to demand it: His Lordſhips head hath ſtood, it ſeems, too long upon his ſhoulders, that makes him he cannot be quiet, till Lieu. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Cromwels charge againſt him, fully proved in the Houſe of Commons, be revived: which is of as high a nature, I beleeve, as ever any charge given in there: The Epitomy of which I have by me; and his Lordſhip may live ſhortly to ſee it in print, by my meanes. And the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburne</hi> in the Book and page laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in ſcandall and diſhonour to <hi>Henry,</hi> Earle of <hi>Stamford,</hi> a Peere of this Kingdome, and late a Commander of Forces of the Parliament, maketh this ſcandalous expreſſion concerning the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Stamford, viz.</hi> And for my Lord of <hi>Stamford</hi> at preſent; I deſire him to remember but one Article made at the delivery of
<hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceter;</hi> which, it may be, may in time coole his furious endeavour to inflame the free people of <hi>England.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="article">
                           <head>III.</head>
                           <p>VVHereas the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburne,</hi> upon the 10. day of Iune laſt paſt, by vertue of the Order of the Peeres aſſembled in this preſent Parliament; was brought to the Barre of the Houſe of Peeres, then ſitting in Parliament; to anſwer concerning the ſaid Book, in the ſaid firſt Article mentioned: the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburne</hi> falſly and maliciouſly intending to ſcandalize and diſhonour the Peeres aſſembled in Parliament, and their juſt rights and authorities; did then and there in contempt of the ſaid Houſe of Peeres, at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Barre of the ſaid Houſe, the Peeres then ſitting in the ſaid Houſe in Parliament; openly deliver a certain paper hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113893:16"/> under his hand and ſeale, intituled, <hi>The Proteſtation, Plea, and Defence of Lieu. Colonell John Lilburne, given to the Lords at their Barre, the 11. of June</hi> 1646. with his appeale to his competent, proper and legall Tryers and Judges, the Commons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parliament: (which paper is hereunto annexed,) and ſince cauſed the ſame to be printed and publiſhed. In which paper, among other ſcandals therein contained, he publiſhed and affirmed, concerning the Lords in Parliament, theſe words following, <hi>Viz.</hi> Therefore, my Lords, you being (as you are) called Peeres, meerly made by prerogative, and never intruſted of improved by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England.</hi> And in another place thereof concerning their Lordſhips, and their proceedings in Parliament; did proteſt and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh theſe words following: I doe here at your open Barre, proteſt againſt all your preſent proceedings with me in this pretended cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall cauſe; as unjuſt, and againſt the tenor and form of the great Charter: which all you have ſworn inviolably to obſerve, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Commons of <hi>England</hi> to doe the ſame: And therefore, my Lords, I doe hereby declare, and am reſolved, as in duty bound to God, my ſelfe, countrey, and poſterity; to maintain my legall liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the laſt drop of my blood, againſt all oppoſers whatſoever; having ſo often in the field, &amp;c. adventured my life there-for: and doe from you and your Barre, as incroachers, and uſurping Judges, appeale to the Barre and Tribunall of my competent, proper, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Tryers and Judges, the Commons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And in purſuance of his ſaid malicious and illegall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; did afterwards contrive and publiſh a ſcandalous and libell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous letter hereunto likewiſe annexed, directed to Mr. <hi>Wollaſton,</hi> Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of <hi>Newgate,</hi> or his Deputy: wherein (among other things) he hath cauſed to be inſerted and publiſhed theſe words concerning the Peeres in Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Lordſhips ſitting by vertue of Prerogative-patents, and not by election or conſent of the people; have (as <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other good lawes of the Land tell me) nothing to doe to try me, or any Commoner whatſoever, in any criminall cauſe, either for life, limb, liberty, or eſtate: But contrary hereunto as incroachers and uſurpers upon my freedomes and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; they lately and illegally endeavoured to try me (a Commoner) at their Barre. For which I under my hand and ſeale, proteſted to their faces againſt them as violent and illegall incroachers upon the <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113893:17"/> Rights and Liberties of me, and all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> (a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of which, &amp;c. I herewith in print ſend you. And at their Barre I openly appealed to my competent, proper, legall Tryers, and Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the Commons of
<hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parliament. For which, their Lordſhips did illegally, arbitrarily, and tyrannically commit me to priſon into your cuſtody, Which Proteſtation, and Papers, and matters therein contained, doe falſly, and ſcandalouſly, and maliciouſly, charge the Peeres in Parliament, with tyranny, uſurpation, perjury, injuſtice, and breach of the great truſt in them repoſed; and are a high breach of the Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And are high offences againſt the Lawes and Statutes of this Kingdome, and doe tend to the great ſcandall of the ſaid Peeres, and the authority with which they are intruſted, &amp; to ſtir up differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between the ſaid Peeres, and other the Subjects of this Realme.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Natha. Finch.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113893:17"/> Vpon which Articles, he refuſing to hear them read, as concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning their proceedings againſt him to be illegall, and that as a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner of England,</hi> they had no juriſdiction over him, they proceeded to ſentence him, as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div n="10 July 1646" type="sentence">
                        <head>
                           <date>Iuly 10. 1646.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>JT is to be remembred, that the 10. day of</hi> Iuly,
<hi>in the 22. Year of the Raign of our Soveraign Lord King</hi> Charles,
<hi>Sir</hi> Nath. Finch <hi>Knight, His Majeſties Serjeant at Law, did deliver in before the Lords aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament at</hi> VVeſtminſter, <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Articles againſt Lieutenant-Colonell</hi> Iohn Lilburn, <hi>for high Crimes and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours, done, and committed by him; together with certain Bookes and Papers thereunto annexed: Which Articles, aad the ſaid Bookes and Papers thereunto annexed, are filed among the Records of Parliament; The tenour of which Articles followeth in theſe words.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113893:18"/> Which Articles being by the command of the Lords, then, and there aſſembled in Parliament, read; It was then, and there, that is to ſay, the ſaid 10. day of <hi>July,</hi> by their Lordſhips ordered, That the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> be brought to the Bar of this Houſe, the 11. day of the ſaid <hi>July,</hi> to anſwer the ſaid Articles; That thereupon their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips might proceed therein, according as to Juſtice ſhould apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
                        <p>At which day aforeſaid, the 11. day of <hi>July, Anno Dom.</hi> 1646. the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> according to the ſaid Order, was brought before the Peers then aſſembled, and ſitting in Parliament; to anſwer the ſaid Articles; And the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> being thereupon required by the ſaid Peers in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to kneel at the Bar of the ſaid houſe, as is uſed in ſuch Caſes, and to hear his ſaid Charge read; to the end, that he might be inabled to make defence thereunto;</p>
                        <p>The ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> in contempt and ſcorn of the ſaid high Court, did not only refuſe to kneel at the ſaid Bar; but did alſo, in a contemptuous manner, then, and there, at the open Barre of the ſaid Houſe, openly and contemptuouſly, refuſe to heare the ſaid Articles read, and uſed divers contemptuous words in high derogation of the Juſtice, Dignity, and Power of the ſaid Court: And the ſaid Charge being nevertheleſſe, then, and there read, the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> was then and there by the ſaid Lords aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> demanded what Anſwer or Defence he would make thereunto; the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> perſiſting in his obſtinate and contemptuous behaviour, did peremptorily, and abſolutely refuſe to make any Defence or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſaid Articles, and did then, and there, in high contempt of the ſaid Court, and of the Peers there aſſembled, at the open Bar of the ſaid Houſe of Peers, affirme, that they were Uſurpers, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Judges; and that he would not anſwer the ſaid Articles, and uſed divers other inſolent and contemptuous ſpeeches againſt their Lordſhips, and that high Court.</p>
                        <p>Whereupon the Lords <hi>aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> taking into their ſerious conſideration the ſaid contemptuous carriage and words of the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> to the great affront, and contempt of this high and honourable Court, and the Juſtice, Authority, and Dignity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;</p>
                        <p>It is therefore this preſent 11. day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> ordered and adjudged by the Lords aſſembled in Parliament;</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113893:18"/> That the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> be Fined; And the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> by the <hi>Lords aſſembled in PARLIAMENT,</hi> for his ſaid contempt, is Fined to the Kings Majeſty, in the ſumme of two thouſand pounds.</p>
                        <p>And it is further ordered and adjudged by the ſaid
<hi>Lords aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> for his ſaid contempts be, and ſtand committed to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> during the pleaſure of the ſaid Houſe.</p>
                        <p>And further, the ſaid <hi>Lords aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> taking into conſideration the ſaid contemptuous refuſall of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> to make any Defence or Anſwer to the ſaid Articles; did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,</p>
                        <p>That the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> ought not thereby to eſcape the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Houſe; But the ſaid Articles, and the Offences thereby charged to have been committed by the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> ought thereupon to be taken as conſeſſed.</p>
                        <p>Wherefore the <hi>Lords aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> taking the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes into conſideration; and for that it appeares by the ſaid Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</p>
                        <p>That the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> hath not onely maliciouſly publiſhed ſeverall ſcandalous, and libellous paſſages of a very high nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Peers of Parliament,</hi> therein particularly named, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Peerage of this Realm in generall, But contrived, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly publiſhed, and openly, at the Barre of the Houſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered certain ſcandalous Papers, to the high contempt and ſcandall, of the Dignity, Power, and Authority of this Houſe.</p>
                        <p>All which offences, by the peremptory refuſall of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> to anſwer, or make any Defence to the ſaid Articles, ſtands confeſſed by the ſaid <hi>Lilburn,</hi> as they are in the ſaid Articles charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</p>
                        <p>It is therefore, the ſaid Day and Year laſt above-mentioned, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordered and adjudged by the <hi>Lords aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> upon the whole matter in the ſaid Articles contained;</p>
                        <p n="1">I. That the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> be Fined to the Kings Majeſty in the ſumme of two thouſand pounds.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113893:19"/> II. And that he ſtand, and be impriſoned in the Tower of <hi>London</hi> by the ſpace of 7. years, now next enſuing.</p>
                        <p n="3">III. And further, that he the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> from henceforth ſtand and be uncapable to bear any Office or Place, in Military, or in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill-Government, in Church or Common-Wealth, during his life.</p>
                        <div n="11 July 1646" type="part">
                           <head>
                              <date>Die Sabbathi 11. Julii 1646.</date>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament; That</hi> Iohn Lilburn <hi>being ſentenced by this Houſe, (ſhall for his high Contempt and Miſdemenors done to this High Court) according to the ſaid Sentence ſtand commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>for the ſpace of 7. Years, next after the date hereof; And that the Lieutenant of the ſaid Tower of</hi> London, <hi>his Deputy, or Deputies, are to keep him in ſafe cuſtody accordingly. And that he doth take care, that the ſaid</hi> Lilburn
<hi>do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113893:19"/> contriue, publiſh, or ſpread any ſeditious or libellous Pamphlets, againſt both, or either of the Houſes of Parliament.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <trailer>To the Lieutenant of the Tower of
<hi>London,</hi> his Deputy, or Deputies.</trailer>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And becauſe this Sentence was conceived not to be ſevere enough by the Lieutenant of the Tower, hee did procure an Order, dated <hi>Die Mercurii 15. Julii,</hi> 1646. which followes in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div n="15 July 1646" type="order">
                        <head>
                           <date>Die Mercurii 15. Iulii, 1646.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament aſſembled, That none ſhall ſpeak with</hi> John Lilburn, <hi>now a priſoner in the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>but in the preſence and hearing of his Keeper, And that when he ſhall deſire to take the Ayre within the Tower, his Keeper ſhall conſtantly goe with him, forth, and back, and ſtay with him, till he return to his Lodging; and that if his wife deſire to come to him, ſhe ſhall reſide with him, and not go in, and out, during his impriſonment in the ſaid Tower. And laſtly, it is Ordered, That this reſtraint of ſpeaking with the ſaid</hi> Lilburn <hi>ſhall be taken off, when he ſhall give good Bayle to this Houſe not to contrive, write, or publiſh any ſcandalous, or libellous Pamphlets, or Papers, againſt both, or either of the Houſes of Parliament.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113893:20"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div n="16 September 1646" type="order">
                        <head>
                           <date>Die Mercurii 16. Septem. 1646.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IT is this day Ordered by the Lords in Parliament aſſembled, That the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naut of the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>his Deputy, and all others imployed him, ſhall permit and ſuffer the wife of Lieutenant-Colonell</hi> Iohn Lilburn, <hi>to come to him, and reſide with him, when, and as often, as he ſhall deſire, any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Order of this Houſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iohn Brown, Cler. Parliamentorum.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>We will not ſay their Lordſhips are unjuſt in this Sentence; yet we hope it ſhall not be accounted ſcandall to them, if we ſay, and make it appear, that they have erred therein, both in manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, and in ſubſtance of matter, or point of juriſdiction, both of the perſon and cauſe; for we do preſume, that their Lordſhips will not preſume an infallibility of Judgment, it being a quality incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible to, or with any ſublunary creatures; and wee finde by our bookes of 21. <hi>E. 3. f</hi> 46. that a Parliament may, and hath erred.</p>
            <p>And firſt, we ſhall declare their Lordſhips errour, in their manner of proceeding againſt this worthy Patriot; wherein we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That the 10. of <hi>Iune,</hi> he was ſummoned to attend their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in their houſe: The 11. of <hi>Iune</hi> he appeared, and was then committed by their Lordſhips to <hi>Newgate.</hi> The 16. of the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth he appealed to the Right Honourable Houſe of Commons. The
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113893:20"/> 22. their Lordſhips ſent to the Keeper of
<hi>Newgate,</hi> to bring him to their Bar; And thereupon the 43 day, he was committed cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner to <hi>Newgate,</hi> being brought by the Keeper of <hi>Newgate,</hi> where he remained cloſe priſoner till the 16, of
<hi>Iuly:</hi> At which time, his Charge was brought into the Lords Houſe, and not before. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, we are firſt to note, that he was ſummoned and committed a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth before his Charge brought in, and after his appeal, and for that cauſe, made cloſe priſoner 18. dayes before any Charge recorded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him;</p>
            <p>All which proceedings, are erroneous, and principally in theſe two points.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe he was ſummoned, before his Charge was recorded: for, regularly, both in Law and Equity, the Declaration or Bill ought to be filed or recorded, before any Writ or Proceſſe ought to iſſue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Defendant or Party accuſed, either in civill or criminall cauſes; and the Writor Proceſſe ought to contain the matter of the Declaration or Bill, as in a <hi>Writ of Right.</hi> Theſe words, <hi>Quid clamat tenere,</hi> import a <hi>Count,</hi> or Declaration recorded; ſo a
<hi>Writ of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia Diei,</hi> contains the ſubſtance of the
<hi>Count,</hi> in a <hi>Monſtraverunt,</hi> the <hi>Plaintiffs</hi> title is ſet forth by the <hi>Writ:</hi> Nay, in every <hi>Writ</hi> at
<hi>Common-Law,</hi> the <hi>Writ</hi> doth by theſe words, <hi>ut dicitur,</hi> or by ſome other Emphaticall word contained in the body of the
<hi>Writ</hi> import, that a Declaration or <hi>Count</hi> is filed, regiſtred, or recorded, before the <hi>Writ</hi> doth iſſue; and this appears clearly in every Writ, ſet forth by the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> and
<hi>Fitzherberts Natura brevium;</hi> Nay, every Engliſh Bill either in
<hi>Chancery, Exchequer,</hi> or <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> doth pray, that
<hi>Proceſſe</hi> of <hi>Sub-paena,</hi> be awarded againſt the Defendant, which proves, that <hi>proceſſe</hi> ought not to be awarded againſt any man out of any Court till his charge bee recorded againſt him in the ſame Court.</p>
            <p>If this was ſo in the Juſtice of the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> in criminal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, we hope their Lordſhips will not condemne it, as an Injuſtice in themſelves, to follow the ſame Rules of Right, Reaſon, Law, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, their Lordſhips proceedings againſt him, after his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal made to the honourable houſe of Commons, were void in Law; <hi>for by the Appeal to the proper juriſdiction, the Lords were outed of their juriſdiction, or Connuſans of the Plea, (ſublata cauſa tollitur effectus)</hi> 
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113893:21"/> the Cauſe being removed by the Appeale, their judgment thereby was determined, or at leaſt ſuſpended, being but the effect of the cauſe before them, till ſuch time as the Appeal is determined, the Appeal being a <hi>ſuperſedas</hi> to their Lordſhips further legall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the ſame cauſe, and wherein they ought not to have procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded without the privity, licence, and direction of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and therefore all their proceedings ſince Mr. <hi>Lilburns</hi> Ap. peal preſented to, and accepted by the houſe of Commons, are <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram non judice,</hi> and therefore void and erroneous.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not deny the Lords houſe to be a Court of Juſtice, and that of Record too, and of the higheſt degree in the Kingdom,
<hi>co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating with the honourablt Houſe of Commons:</hi> but when they are diſtinct, and apart in their ſeverall operations and judgments; we do conceive, that they neither have <hi>a legiſlative nor unlimitted power of judicature in themſelves;</hi> neither can they proceed to determine any thing out of the way of the known Lawes, by any <hi>arbitrary, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretionary Rules,</hi> where there is a known Law in the caſe.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edw Cook</hi> doth well ſet forth the diſtinct powers of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of both houſes, in his 4. part of <hi>Inſtitutes, p.</hi>
23.</p>
            <p>It is to be known, ſaith he, that the Lords in their houſe, have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Judicature, <hi>and both Houſes together have power of Iudicature,</hi> which is thus to be underſtood, <hi>That the Lords have power of Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature over their Members alone,</hi> viz. <hi>their Peers, the Nobility of England that ſit in the Lords Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Commons have power of Iudicature over all the Commons of England, by themſelves alone; and the Lords and Commons joyning have power of Iudicature over both Peers Lords, and Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this is true, is manifeſt by the Lord <hi>Dacres caſe, p.</hi> 26, <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>reported by Iuſtice Spilman,</hi> where it was reſolved, that a Noble-man of Parliament, cannot wave his tryall by his Peers, and put himſelfe upon the tryall of the Country: for by the Statute of
<hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, c.</hi> 29 every man is to be tryed, <hi>per legale judicium parium ſuorum,</hi> by the lawfull judgment of his Peers; which Statute, gives the Lords of Parliament a juriſdiction over their Peers, which cannot be taken from them; and as the Lords have a juriſdiction over their Peers; ſo have the Commons over their Peers, <hi>viz.</hi> all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of
<hi>England:</hi> for, <hi>as Sir Edw Cook</hi> 2. <hi>part. of his Inſtitutes, pag.</hi> 29. in his Coment upon <hi>Magna Charta c.</hi> 14. obſerves, that the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <pb n="39" facs="tcp:113893:21"/> diviſion of perſons, by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> is either into the Nobility of the Peerage, (or Lords, houſe) or the Commons of the Realm: for as every of the Nobles is a Peer to each other, though they have ſeverall Names of Dignity, as <hi>Dukes, Marquiſſes, Earles, Viſcounts,</hi> and <hi>Barons;</hi> ſo of the Commons of the Realme, each Commoner is a Peer or Equall to another, though they be of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Degrees, as <hi>Knights, Eſquites, Citizens, Gentlemen, Yeomen,</hi> and <hi>Rurgeſſes:</hi> and this diſtinction we find likewiſe in <hi>Bracton, c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſol.</hi> 36. and both theſe Juriſdictions do belong to both Houſes, <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali equitate,</hi> by a naturall right or equity, as hereafter more plainly will be demonſtrated: and according to this Juriſdiction, have the Commons themſelves given judgment upon a Commoner, as in the caſe of <hi>Thomas Longe,</hi> cited by Sir
<hi>Edward Cooke, vbi ſupra, p.</hi> 23. and recorded in the Journall Book of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, 8. <hi>Eliz. Onſlow</hi> Speaker, <hi>f.</hi> 19. and in the caſe of <hi>Arthur Hall,</hi> 23 <hi>Eliz. f.</hi> 14.
<hi>Popham,</hi> Attorney General, Speaker, and divers others.</p>
            <p>Now, that the Lords and Commons have a joynt Juriſdiction, or power of Judicature over both Lords and Commons, is manifeſt by the Judgments given againſt the Lord <hi>Audley,</hi> at the Parliament held at <hi>Yorke, Anno</hi> 12. 22 <hi>Conſideratum eſt per Praelatos, Comites Barones &amp; communitatem Angliae,</hi> and in 15. <hi>E.</hi> 2. the Judgment given againſt the <hi>Spencers,</hi> both Earles, <hi>Hugh</hi> the Father, and
<hi>Hugh</hi> the Son, who were adjudged to exile, by the Lords and Commons, and Sir <hi>John Alees</hi> adjudged by the Lords and Commons, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares 42.
<hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Nu.</hi> 20. <hi>Rot, Parl.</hi> and of late time in the caſes of Sir <hi>Giles Mompeſſon,</hi> the Lord Viſcount of St.
<hi>Alban,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> in 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.
<hi>Iacob. Regis:</hi> In all which Judgements the Kings conſent was concurrent, which gave thoſe Judgments life and efficacy.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſtinguiſhed, the ſeverall and joynt Juriſdiction of both Houſes; it will bee neceſſary to ſhew whence theſe have ſprung, and how they are grown. It appears by the old Treatiſe, <hi>de modo tenendi Parliamentum,</hi> which was made before the Conqueſt, and preſented to the Conquerour, who held a Parliament in that forme, as appeares by the book of 21. E. 3. <hi>f.</hi> 60. <hi>That both Houſes of Parliament</hi> ſate together, and were but in effect one Houſe, and ſo continued long after the Conqueſt, till 5. and 6.
<hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>as</hi> appears <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113893:22"/> by the Parliament Rolls of 5. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Nu.</hi> 3. and 6. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and by the 4. part of Sir <hi>Edward Cookes Inſtit. p.</hi> 2. and as may be gathered by the Preamble to the Statute of <hi>Marlebridge,</hi> made 52. <hi>H.</hi> 3.
<hi>Weſtm.</hi> the firſt, 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 2. 13,
<hi>E.</hi> 1, the Statute of <hi>Yorke,</hi> made 12. <hi>E.</hi> 2. and others, which mention, that the Prelates, Earles, Barons, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty of the Realm were called together (whereby we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that they ſate as one Houſe) to conſult of the weighty affaires of this Kingdom; from whence, we collect, that the Lords had whileſt they ſate as one Houſe, no particular juriſdiction, nor the Commons any to themſelves alone, <hi>but their juriſdiction was joynt,</hi> being mixt of both their powers, and communicative to all alike of both Kingdoms; and this appeares cleerly, by the caſe of the Lord <hi>Audley,</hi> 12. <hi>E.</hi> 2. and the cauſe of the
<hi>Spencers,</hi> 15. <hi>E.</hi> 2. afore cited, and by the caſe of
<hi>Nicholas Segrave,</hi> adjudged in Parliament, as appears <hi>Placit: Parliament,</hi> 33. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Rot.</hi> 33. <hi>per Praelatos, Comites, Barones, &amp; alios de conſilio,</hi> by the Prelates, Earles, Barons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Councell, that is, the Parliament; and more plainly by that: ſpoken by Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> 2 <hi>part of his Inſtit. p.</hi> 50. And though of antient time (ſaith he) the Lords and Peers of the Realm uſed in Parliament to give judgment, in caſe of Treaſon and Fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, againſt thoſe that were no Lords of Parliament;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet at the ſuit of the Lords, it was enacted; that albeit the Lords and Peers of the Realm, as Judges of the Parliament, in the preſence of the King, had taken upon them to give judgment in caſe of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Fellony, of ſuch as were not Peers of the Realm, that hereafter no Peers ſhall be driven to give judgment on any others, then on their Peers according to the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he cites <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Nu.</hi> 6. to maintain this aſſertion of his.</p>
            <p>But to conclude more ſtrongly, we find it recorded in 4.
<hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2. and inrolled in Chancery, in the cauſe of Sir
<hi>Simon de Beris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who was adjudged as an acceſſary to <hi>Roger Mortimer</hi> of the murder of King <hi>Ed:</hi> 2. in theſe very words,
<hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it is aſſented, and agreed by our Lord the King, and all the Grandees in full Parliament; that albeit the ſaid Peers, as Judges of Parliament took upon them in the preſence of our Lord the King, to make and give the ſaid judgment, by the aſſent of the King, upon ſome of them which were not their Peers, and that by reaſon of the murder
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113893:22"/> of their liege Lord, and the deſtruction of him which was ſo neare of the Blood-Royall, and Son of a King; that therefore the ſaid Peeres which now are, or the Peeres which ſhall be for the time to come; be not bound or charged to give judgment upon others, then upon their Peers, nor ſhall do it: (But let the Peers of the land have power) but of that forever they be discharged and acquitted, and that the aforeſaid judgment now given be not drawn into example, or conſequence for the time to come; by which the ſaid Peeres may be charged hereafter to judge others then their Peers againſt the Law of the Land, if any ſuch caſe happen</hi> (which God defend.)</p>
            <p>All which afore-mentioned preſidents and judgments were made and given before the ſeparation of the two Houſes &amp; whileſt they ſate together.</p>
            <p>Out of which, we collect and gather, that the Lords had no particular juriſdiction to themſelves, or of themſelves, before the diviſion &amp; ſeparation of the Pouſes; and that it was againſt the Law of the Land, for the Peers before this ſeparation, to judge a Commoner in any caſe whatſoever: Nay, that their hands are bound by their aſſent, never to judge any in future, which Sir <hi>Ed: Cork</hi> ſaith, was enacted:</p>
            <p>So that joyning the one conſideration with the other, it is moſt cleer, that the Peers at this day cannot judge a Commoner; no, not if the King joyn with them; eſpecially, in caſe of life, or free-hold, for in the book of 4 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>f.</hi> 10. <hi>Be tit. Parl.</hi> 42. We find that in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the King would that <hi>I. S.</hi> ſhouldbe attainted, and loſe his Land, and the Lords did agree, and nothing was ſpoken of the Commons; and this by all the Judges was held no good attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or judgment, and therefore he was reſtored to his Lands: for there can be no attainder by Parliament, but by Act of Parliament, that is, by judgment of both Houſes, and conſent of the King: for the King, as Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> ſaith, is of the Parliament, <hi>caput prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium, &amp; finis,</hi> the head, the beginning, and the end.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, that the Lords have a Judicature a-part from the Commons, which they have long uſed: It is true, they have, and it is only in ſome particular caſes, and their power is given them by Act of Parliament, by the ſtature of 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. in caſe of delay of Juſtice, difficulty of judgment, or caſes of errours, and is confirmed unto them by the ſtature of 25. <hi>El. c.</hi> 8. and 31. <hi>El. c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:113893:23"/> But we cannot find by any of our bookes in Law, and wee are confident, no man can ſhew us, that the Lords by themſelves apart or without the aſſiſtance, and without judgment of the Commons, did hold plea in any of thoſe caſes; before that ſtatute of 14.
<hi>E.</hi> 3. For the firſt caſes that we find of any proceedings in thoſe caſes before the Lords, were in 16. <hi>E. 3. Fitzh. tit. briefe,</hi> 561. and in 24. <hi>E. 3. f. 46. 22. E. 3. Fitz. error</hi> 8. and other bookes; out of which good notes may be drawn to fortifie our aſſertions withall, if need in ſo plain a caſe did require: By all which caſes and preſidents, we may aſſuredly conclude.
<q rend="margQuotes">That the Lords in their Houſe have no juriſdiction over the Commons in any other caſes, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of Juſtice, difficulty of Judgment, or matter of Errour, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And this is agreeable to the ſtatute of 25. <hi>E. 3. c.</hi> 4. Where it is accorded, aſſented, and eſtabliſhed,
<q rend="margQuotes">that from hence-forth, none ſhall be taken by petition, or ſuggeſtion, made to our Lord the King, or to his Councell; unleſſe it be by indictment, or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his good and lawfull people of the ſame neighborhood, or by proceſſe made by Writ originall at the common-law, and to the other ſtatutes afore-mentioned, and bindes the Houſe of Peers, as well as any other Court of Judicature at
<hi>Westminſter,</hi> as they are of the Kings Councell, and ſit by vertue of the Kings writ and Commiſſion, as they have often by their own Declarations manifeſted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If it be objected, that their Lordſhips being a Court of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are only to proceed, <hi>ſecundum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti,</hi> according to the Law and Cuſtome of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>We anſwer, that we grant that it muſt be <hi>ſecundum legem,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to law, which is, according to the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> and the laws before cited; and as touching the cuſtome of Parliament; we ſay that the Lords houſe cannot have any pretence by cuſtome to judge a Commoner of <hi>England,</hi> ſince that it appeares by the preſidents afore-mentioned: namely, Sir <hi>Simon de Berisfords</hi> caſe which was 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and by that of the ſame date, cited out of Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> that before the diviſion of the Houſes, it was enacted, and aſſented, that the Peers for the time to come, ſhould not judge a Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; as being againſt Law, as aforeſaid: And therefore, that Cuſtome being againſt Law, and prohibited by Act of Parliament,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113893:23"/> muſt needs be void in Law: For no Cuſtome that is againſt Law or an Act of Parliament, <hi>is valid in Law:</hi> Neither can they have any good Cuſtom by uſage of ſuch power, ſince the diviſion of th, Houſes, though they have actually judged Commoners, it being within time of memory ſince the Houſes were divided: that is to ſay, ſince the time of King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, which is the limitation of preſcriptions; and ſince which time, no good cuſtome can bee grounded, the contrary appearing by matter of Record, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>And albeit, they have judged Commoners; it makes not for them; for, <hi>a facto ad jus non valer argumentum,</hi> becauſe they have done it in fact; therefore, they may now do it of right, followes not: For, if thoſe Commoners that were judged by them, did not ſtand upon their priviledge, nor demand an exemption from the judgment of the Lords, they did only loſe to themſelves the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular benefit of Appeale: for, <hi>vigilantibus, &amp; non dormientibus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſubveniunt:</hi> the lawes only aſſiſt thoſe that claime the benefit of them, &amp; not thoſe that pray not in aid of them: and ſuch preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents ought not to be cited, in prejudice of others that are more watchfull over their liberties.</p>
            <p>But wee have another objeſtion made, that there is matter of ſcandall againſt a Peer of that Houſe, contained in Mr.
<hi>Lilburres</hi> Charge, and therefore fit to be examined there,</p>
            <p>We acknowledge the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> to be a perſon of great honour, and will not blemiſh him, as he ſtands unheard, with a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of his being guilty: But nevertheleſſe, we conceive that it would not have leſſened his honour, to have preferred ſome Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in the Kings Bench, or brought ſome Action at Common-Law upon ſome of the ſtatutes, <hi>de ſcandalis magnatum,</hi> for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſlander contained in the bookes, written by Mr.
<hi>Lilburn,</hi> whereunto Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> might have pleaded his lawfull plea, either by may of juſtification, or deniall, as his caſe would require him: In both which caſes Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> ſhould have been tryed by a Jury of 12 honeſt men, Commoners, his equals: and my Lord have avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any ſuſpition of being partiall in his own cauſe, as it is ſaid in the book of 8. <hi>H. 6. f. 14. Br. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſans,</hi> 27. of the Chancellour of <hi>Oxford,</hi> or that he went about by this ſo ſudden and ſummary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to hinder or fore-ſtall the evidence that might bee againſt <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113893:24"/> him in his own cauſe, and Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> had had a legall way for his defence: for if he had juſtified the ſuppoſed ſcandall, and proved it, it had bin no ſcandal, &amp; the Jury muſt have acquitted him, if he had pleaded not guilty: and for the words proved againſt him, he muſt have paid dammage to the Earle, as the Jury ſhould have aſſeſſed. And this had been, and is the only way of tryal in ſuch a caſe, and is according to the ſtatute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Law of the Land; and it is a Maxime in Law, <hi>That where remedy may bee had by an ordinary courſe in Law, the partie grieved ſhall never have his recourſe to extraordinaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, if a man ſhould ſay of the Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keeper of the Great Seal, that he was a corrupt Judge, and that he gave a corrupt judgment in ſuch a Cauſe depending before him, upon an Engliſh Bill in Chancery; The Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keepers remedy againſt that perſon for this ſcandal; is upon theſe ſtatutes, and not by an Engliſh Bill in Chancery before himſelf, to be proved only by witneſſes, or (the Parliament ſitting) by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and not by a Jury, being matter of Fact, tryable by the courſe of the common-law: Neither doe we conceive, that this ſcandall reflects upon that noble Earl (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f it be ſo) as he is a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Lords houſe but as a Generall of an Army, which em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, he had as well from the Commons, as the Lords, and the rather, ſince one of the Commons is as capable, as a Peer of the Lords houſe, of ſuch a Command.</p>
            <p>Therefore, we conclude, as to the matter and manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this ſentence upon the Lieutenant-Colonell, may be taken to be erroneous, both concerning the nature of the cauſe, and the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Court; in reſpect of the Defnedants priviledge; not to be judged by the Lords Houſe, being a Commoner of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> unleſſe the Commons had firſt enquired of the offence, and had tranſmitted it to the Lords Houſe, upon a vote made in their Houſe, by information or impeachment; together, with the proofs taken by them in the Cauſe; but eſpecially, after an Appeal made to the Houſe of Commons, as his proper Judges:</p>
            <p>But we meet with another objection, which is; that part of this ſentence, is for words and contempts acted after his ſummons to the Lords Houſe, and at his appearing there: one of which was, for not kneeling at the Lords Barre; for that we conceive, that if hee <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113893:24"/> through the tenderneſſe of Conſcience, not to offend God, by kneeling to any other power, did refuſe to kneel at their Barre, (though it be a cuſtome for thoſe that are brought thither as Delinquents ſo to do: We cannot conceive that to bee a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, but rather an obedience to him,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he ought to obey rather then men. As touching the no hearing of his Charge read, it was after his Appeal, Plea, and Defence, delivered in: which if that were juſt, and now reſt; to be determined by the honourable Houſe of Commons, and by them ſo adjudged; there could be no contempt in that: And therefore, till his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale be determined, wee conceive, that part of his Sentence might well have been ſpared: As touching the contemptuous words by him uttered, againſt the proceedings of that honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Court, though we cannot excuſe it, <hi>a toto,</hi> yet <hi>a tanto,</hi> we may, in that they were rather words of heat proceeding from him, upon deniall of his Plea and Defence, which was his appeale to the honourable Houſe of Commons, as his proper Judges, and rather iſſuing from him, out of a ſence of his conceived injury, then a ſpirit of calumny towards their Lordſhips: We are of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that in that ſence they might have produced a more mild ſentence, then to have been his utter ruine; ſince by that ſentence he is to have 7. yeares impriſonment (the age of a man in the eye of the Law) and be made incapable of bearing any Office, Military or Civill, in the Army or Common-Wealth, and to be fined 4000.
<hi>l.</hi> which we think, is more then he is able to pay: wheras by the ſtatute of <hi>Magna Charta, liber homo non amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietur, pro parvo delicto, niſi ſecundum modum illius delicti &amp; pro magno delicto, ſecundum magnitudinem illius delicti, ſalvo ſibi conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemento ſuo;</hi> If his offence were great; yet hee ought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merced, ſo as his free-hold &amp; contenement, or countenance may be ſaved to him, and not to be diſabled in his Calling, or lodged in the Tower, during his life, where he now remains.</p>
            <p>Having brought this indomitable Champion for our liberties, to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> wee will ſhew you his entertainment there;</p>
            <p>He was brought by the Warders to the Lieutenant, <hi>alias dictus</hi> Col. <hi>Francis Weſt,</hi> the Gaoler, or chiefe Keeper of the Priſon of the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> for ſo his title is, in the capacity of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113893:25"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113893:25"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:113893:26"/> and keeping of the Priſoners committed to his charge; This <hi>Lieutenant</hi> or
<hi>Goaler</hi> after ſome pauſe upon reading of the Warrant of Commitment, ſent him to lodge at a Warders houſe for his further puniſhment,
<hi>where he is to pay neere 20. s. a weeke for his lodgeing,</hi> providing himſelfe dyet; The <hi>Lieutenant</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad his Keeper to let any body at firſt to come to ſpeake with him, and forgetting the rule of Gods word,
<hi>whom God hath joyned together let no man ſeparate or keepe aſunder,</hi> upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that by the Lords ſentence and his Warrant, he could not keepe that worthy <hi>Patriot,</hi> from informing the people of their liberties, which the ſaid <hi>Goaler</hi> or
<hi>Lieutenant</hi> called writing of ſcandalous bookes againſt the Lords, unleſſe he kept his wife and his friends from him, notwithſtanding that
<q rend="margQuotes">Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Lilburne</hi> offered to engage his word to the ſaid Gaoler not to write any word-book, or letter, either of or concerning both, or either Houſe of Parliament,</q> or any thing elſe of publike concernment, ſo he might have his wife and Children, and friends admitted to him, according to law and right, anſwer was thereupon made by the ſame Gaoler.
<q rend="margQuotes">That unleſſe his wife would ſtay with him and remaine with him as a cloſe priſoner to be kept within the Tower, he cold not permit her to come to him, to ſtay with him, or ſpeake with him, but in the preſence of his keeper</q>, (the firſt time that ever we heard that the innocent wife was to be impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and puniſhed for the Husbands offence) having at that time no warrant to reſtraine either his wives or friends coming to him; but to colour ſuch his illegall, uncharitable, and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlike dealings, he goes to the Lords, and procutes order from them as a ſuperſtructure upon the former ſentence, to keepe this worthy Gentlemans wife from him, and not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to ſtay with him, or to ſpeake with him but in the preſence of his Keeper:
<q rend="margQuotes">O horrible and unheard of Cruelty, and barbariſme, did not God make woman of man, that ſhe might be an helper unto him meete for him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 18.</q> 
               <hi>did not God ordaine them to be one fleſh,</hi> did not our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſay,
<q rend="margQuotes">that God from the begining had made them male, and female, and that after their marriage they are no more twaine, but one fleſh: doth he not command, and is it not</q> 
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:113893:26"/> an ordinance indiſpenſable, <hi>That what God hath joyned together, let no man put aſunder, Matth.</hi> 19, 4, 5, 6. By what power or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority doth this
<hi>Goaler</hi> take upon him to diſpenſe with, nay, to change the immutable laws of God our maker, and of our Saviour and Redeemer? If ye have faith in him, doth not our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tell the wicked Jews, when they tempted him with this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſtion, <hi>Is it lawfull for a man to put away his wife? THAT IT WAS NOT LAWFVLL:</hi> And that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuffered the Jewes through the hardneſſe of their h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arts, to put away their wives; <hi>But from the beginning it was not ſo?</hi> If this were hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart for a man to put away his wife, though with her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; how much more, and how much greater hardneſſe of heart is it, that a woman, innocent and not charged at all with the offences of her husband that was created to be an helper to him, ſhould, in the time of his impriſonment and affliction when hee needs moſt help, either be kept from him in a conjugall way, or if ſhe will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with him, muſt be made partaker of his puniſhments, if they were juſtly impoſed? which kind of condition was never im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the wife of any man attainted or convicted of <hi>treaſon, felony,</hi> or
<hi>murder.</hi> For, though a man is attainted of treaſon that hath a wife; their marriage is not thereby diſſolved: neither can they be kept aſunder. Therefore we may conclude, that this uſage of this ſuffering Gentleman for the publick liberty, is both againſt the <hi>Lawes of God, Nature,</hi> and <hi>Man:</hi> Againſt the lawes of God and Nature, as againſt the end of our creation: Againſt the Lawes of Chriſt, as againſt his ordinances: Againſt the law of man, as it is againſt the law of God, Nature, and the law of the Land.</p>
            <p>And here we ſhall leave this worthy Gentleman ſuffering un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this tyrany, and extream oppreſſion of this <hi>Goaler,</hi> (who hath choſen rather to obey men then God;) who, if he be offended that we call him
<hi>Goaler;</hi> we are able to inform him, that a predeceſſor of his own, Sir <hi>Gervaſe Elviſh,</hi> who was Lieutenant of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>(tam amlpis modo &amp; formae)</hi> as he now is, was indicted by the name of
<hi>Goaler of the Tower of London,</hi> and hanged upon <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> for conſenting to the poyſoning of his priſoner Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury.</hi> Taking occaſion upon this uſage of this Gentleman, to declare unto you, as we have been credibly informed from perſons of good quality; the politick government of the <hi>Guardian</hi> of this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113893:27"/> priſon, and his <hi>Warders,</hi> for exacting money out of their priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, when a priſoner comes new in, or that is committed thither, and not yet come; an Enqueſt is made by the Warders, what that priſoner is, what eſtate he hath, and whether he be like to pay wel; and if he be, each man is a ſuiter to the Lieutenant, that he may have the keeping of him: Perhaps if he be a good <hi>Fat one indeed,</hi> a Bribe is given, or ſome Reward promiſed at leaſt, to the Gentleman <hi>Goaler,</hi> (a new erected Office, and an intruded Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, as we ſhall ſhew hereafter) to procure the cuſtody of that priſoner. If a Bribe or a Reward be not given; then the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant beſtowes the priſoner upon his Warders, as they are in favour with him: as the great <hi>Turk</hi> doth his Concubines upon his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes. And then the Warder is obliged to ſerue his priſoner for the
<hi>Lieutenants</hi> advantage; which hee commonly doth by theſe courſes: Firſt, he is kept cloſe priſoner for ten or twelve dayes, or more, not ſuffered by their good wills, to ſpeake with any body but themſelves, for feare leſt they ſhould bee informed how to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade their ſnares. In which time, the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> tells the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that he hath placed him with an honeſt Keeper in his favour: And the Keeper tells him, that the
<hi>Lieutenant</hi> is a very noble Gentleman, that he will deſire nothing but what is due to him by the cuſtome of the place: and brings him to a contract of five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a week, which he claimes for his own fee for attendance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; and 20 ſhillings a week, or thereabouts, for his lodging, if he lodge in the Warders houſe; and of ſome, more; and ſome, leſſe. When that is done, the Warders tell him, <hi>That there are fees due to the Lieutenant:</hi> and deſire them to think of it to prepare their way to a further liberty. (being all this while kept in their Chambers.) Which, when they have contracted for, with their Warders, if they are lodged in their Warders or Keepers Houſes; then they fall to work for the <hi>Lieutenants fees:</hi> and the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> avowes theirs; and ſo <hi>Mulus mulum ſcabit.</hi> This being done, the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> ſends out his Beagles, of which, this <hi>Gentleman Goaler</hi> is alwayes one, being his chiefe Eare-wigge, and of the <hi>Quorum</hi> too; he comes and tells the priſoner, <hi>There are fees due to the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant.</hi> If the priſoner asks, what is due; he will tell you, <hi>that there is</hi> 100. l. <hi>due for the admittance of an Earle,</hi> 80. l. <hi>for a Baron,</hi> 70. l.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113893:27"/> 
               <hi>for a Knight and Baronet,</hi> 60. l. <hi>for a Baronet,</hi> 50. l. <hi>for a Knight, and</hi> 40. l. <hi>for an Eſquire:</hi> and that there is 30. s. <hi>a week to be paid by every priſoner for liberty to buy and dreſſe his own meat.</hi> Where you may obſerve, that here is not onely an exciſe put upon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of perſons of quality; but upon their mouthes too, beſides that which the States have put upon their meat: and that, it ſeems a prepoſterous courſe, that a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſhould be brought perforce to a priſon, and againſt his will, and be inforced to pay for his admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to a <hi>Goale,</hi> as to a <hi>Copy-hold,</hi> or ſome other matter of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. If you will ask him how it appeares theſe fees are due: his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, <hi>That Mr. Lieutenant is not ſo earneſt of mony, but that if the priſoner be not provided, he will ſtay for thoſe fees till you can procure money.</hi> And by this means wring a promiſe out of the priſoner if he can: and if the priſoner give but the leaſt hope of payment, though it lookes not towards any undertaking to pay any of thoſe fees; <hi>This Gentleman Goaler</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to affirm (and ſwear if need be) the priſoners promiſe. Shortly after the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> will (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture) ſend his Clerk to demand your fees and weekly payment of 30. s. which he calls by the name of
<hi>Compoſition money.</hi> And if the priſoner ſtand upon it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that nothing is due: then he will tell you, <hi>You promiſed to pay, and therefore are bound to pay, if there were none due.</hi> But if you ask him, how long thoſe Fees have been paid? He will tell you, <hi>Twenty one yeares;</hi> and that makes a preſcription: whereby we learn, that 21. yeares make a
<hi>Goalers Preſcription. Quodnota benè.</hi> If you return him empty-handed, then he brings you <hi>a thundring meſſage,</hi> or perhaps, letters from his Maſter; wherein he tells you, <hi>If you will not pay the fees demanded, you muſt keep your chamber.</hi> And after that, if you walk but abroad out of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chamber, <hi>hea'l threaten to ſet a Sentinell at your doore</hi> (the firſt time that ever we read of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sentinell</hi> in the office of a <hi>Goaler.)</hi> And afterwards (peradventure) if you pay him not; he comes in perſon to you, and tells you,
<hi>He cannot live without money.</hi> If you ask him, how he proves it to be due, he will tell you, <hi>that he finds it by his Predeceſſors books,</hi> Sir <hi>John Conyers,</hi> and Sir <hi>Allen Apſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys:</hi> and this is Title enough to an extortion.</p>
            <p>Theſe paſſages put us in mind of a Story that we have read in <hi>Rhamuſio,</hi> of a great Deſart in <hi>Tartary,</hi> called
<hi>Lop,</hi> where are ſtore of wild Beaſts; amongſt the reſt, there is one that is like a Lion, <pb n="50" facs="tcp:113893:28"/> but is not, and he hath alwayes two ſmall beaſts, which are called <hi>Jackals,</hi> and are like Foxes, but are not Foxes. Theſe <hi>Jackals,</hi> they follow the prey cloſe at the heeles, and hunt it till it be weary: The greater beaſt followes after grunting at a diſtance. When theſe <hi>Jackals</hi> have wearied the prey, this counterfeit Lion comes, and ſeiſes upon it, and fills his panc, and leaves the reſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the leſſer Whippets; and between the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is no harmleſſe beaſt that is not wholly eaten up, being once ſeiſed on. <hi>Juſt ſo is the poore priſoners caſe.</hi> And we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this further, that as the <hi>Divell,</hi> when hee tempted our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, as you may read, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 6. could cite this part of the Scripture, <hi>Caſt thy ſelfe down, for it is written, He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee:</hi> But concealed another part of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which made againſt his ends, to wit, <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God:</hi> So deales this Lieutenant, or <hi>Grand Goaler, Weſt,</hi> with his priſoners: for, all that makes againſt his title to his fees, he leaves out in his allegation to his priſoners: of which, that he may not plead ignorance hereafter; wee ſhall tell him his pretended title to theſe fees. In the time of Sir <hi>Allen Apſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> much about 21. yeares ſince, when he was. <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the Tower, there were divers priſoners in the Tower that were poor, and lay upon his hands for maintenance, of which hee informed the then Lords of the privie Councell, and petitioned that he might be allowed competency for their maintenance out of the Kings Exchequer. The Lords (according to law) ordered that he ſhould have 3. l. a week, with increaſe according to their qualities, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for each priſoner, to maintain them in diet, (for they being the Kings priſoners, were by law to be maintained by the King.) Sir <hi>Allen Apſley</hi> having procured this order, and ſome of his Succeſſors after him, did contract with ſome of the Warders, or Victuallers in the Tower, to diet thoſe, ſometimes at 30. s. per week, ſometimes at 20. s. per week, ſometimes at 35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> s. a week, as they could agree; whereby Sir <hi>Allen Apſley</hi> put up into his purſe 30. s. a week, or more or leſſe, upon allowance of every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and had his full pay out of the Kings Exchequer. This was entred into their Bookes, as a gain to them. And being grounded upon a Cheat, is now become a preſident of future extortion, being confirmed by a <hi>Goalers Preſcription of 21. yeares.</hi> But wee would <pb n="51" facs="tcp:113893:28"/> have them know, that if every thing that hath been practiſed 21. years bee lawful; they may as well goe to
<hi>Suiters-hill,</hi> and there take purſes as to demand thoſe fees. Beſides, we deſire them to take notice, <hi>that by this Parliament, the foundation of this pretended duty is taken away by that Act of Parliament which takes away the power of the Councell-boord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But wee have done with the pretence of their fees: wee now come to ſhew, that this Office of <hi>Gentleman Goaler,</hi> is a new ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted office, and a grievance to the ſubject, being created within time of memory: and conſequently, no fees due to him, though he pretend to a fee of 50. s. at the priſoners going away, For this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, (one <hi>Yates)</hi> to tell the truth, is but the Lieutenants man; and if he be a <hi>Gentleman Goaler,</hi> it is to be doubted he is a better man then his <hi>Maſter:</hi> for we make a ſcruple, <hi>Whether a PORTER of a Colledge in Biſhopſgate-ſtreet can beget a Gentleman.</hi> But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be, being of an old Yeoman of the Guard, become a young <hi>Gentleman Goaler,</hi> he knowes how to lick his fingers, and <hi>make profit out of the plague it ſelfe.</hi> For wee could tell you, that when a Gentleman the laſt yeare a priſoner, was cloſely locked up, and the plague round about him, and in danger to be infected, deſired him to ſpeak to the Lieutenant, that he might be removed; he brought him word, <hi>that unleſſe he would give him ten pound, hee could not be removed.</hi> The Gentleman made anſwer, that hee had not ſo much money; but all that he had, he would give him, if he would procure him to be removed. The ſumme agreed, was 20. s. which this <hi>Gentleman Goaler</hi> took and put in his pocket, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came at him more in ten weeks ſpace, let the plague take his courſe with the poore priſoner: And that albeit the Gentleman complained to the Lieutenant of this unjuſt and fraudulent dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and did deſire that either he might be compelled to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, or otherwiſe to give it to the poore, or into the Warders Box at Chriſtmas; yet the Gentleman could obtaine neither. Here is <hi>Mulus mulum ſcabit</hi> again. We could tell you, that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon lodgings have been, and are <hi>let out to priſoners at</hi> 20. l. <hi>ſome more, ſome leſſe, per annum.</hi> We could tell you of 10. l. taken of a Gentleman that was ſick, and made a cloſe priſoner, for to have liberty to walk in freſh aire out of his chamber ſome 4. or 5. times the length of a Cannon. We could tell you another, that by no <pb n="52" facs="tcp:113893:29"/> Rule of Inſtruction, or Warrant, was to be kept cloſe priſoner, and yet was ſo almoſt a yeare becauſe he would not give 10. l. to walk the length of a Malt-pole. We could tell you of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of quality, of above 70 yeares of age, after hee had his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement from the Honorable Houſe of Commons, was detained in cloſe priſon 20. weeks, becauſe he would not pay ſuch fees as were demanded; and <hi>a demand of above</hi> 330. l. <hi>made of him for theſe pretended extortions and unjuſt fees:</hi> Nay, <hi>a boord nailed up before his window, to prevent him for taking any freſh aire, and a Sentinell ſet at his doore to keep him in his chamber.</hi> A new way of theſe monſtrous Tyrants, to <hi>exciſe the Aire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We could name a priſoner that for ſix moneths together in the Tower, had a Sentinel kept at his door to keep him in his lodging; yea, when he was ſick, and had contracted that ſickneſſe and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity by a tedious cloſe impriſonment. We could tell of the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Beere and Wood ſtopped, and their ſervants kept from them, <hi>becauſe they would not pay ſuch fees as were demanded:</hi> And when the priſoners ſent to the Lieutenant to have their Beere and Firing; his anſwer was, <hi>That he wanted money.</hi> HERE ARE THE FOURE ELEMENTS EXCISED TO THE POORE PRISONERS. Nay, wee could tell you of ſome that were ſhut up for eating of Veniſon, and to make their peace, muſt drop ſomething, <hi>a parcell of</hi> 20 l <hi>or ſomething elſe:</hi> For we muſt keep our fingers in uſe. Nay, there is but few of theſe ravening creatures, but he hath all the inventions his wit can reach to excoriate their priſoners. We could tell you how priſoners are valued: <hi>Some have been valued at 5. s. a week and diet:</hi> Anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at diet only; a third hath been offered to be <hi>exchanged with 20. s. boot.</hi> Nay, we could tel yon of a priſoner that was made in joincture to a Warders wife, who contracted by Articles upon their mariage, that his wife ſhould have the profits proceeding of his priſoner. Which proceedings puts us in mind of that ſtory we read in
<hi>Lucian,</hi> who ſaith, that <hi>Homer upon a time had drunk too much of the ſweet wine of Chios, his native Countrey, and fell a ſpewing; and there came</hi> Pindarus, <hi>and</hi> Virgil, <hi>and</hi> Homer, <hi>and a great many more, and lickt up his ſpewings, and thereby became inſpired with Poetry, every one according to the quantity of the ſpewings that he lickt up.</hi> So theſe <hi>Goalers,</hi> upon the diſſolution of <hi>Regall Authority,</hi> each of them <pb n="53" facs="tcp:113893:29"/> hath lickt up a part of the ſpewings of it, &amp; are become exerciſers of this illegal arbitrary power, ſo far as their Wits will give them way, to the extream vexation and oppreſſion of their priſoners: Inſomuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the poor priſoners doe wiſh with holy <hi>Job,</hi> That they had been as an hidden untimely Birth, or as Infants that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw light, who are in that place, where the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and the weary be arreſt, where the priſoners reſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they hear not the voice of the oppreſſour: wherefore is light given unto him that is in miſery, and life unto the bitter in ſoule?
<hi>Job.</hi> 3. 16, 17, 18, 20. Yet, tell Mr. <hi>White</hi> one of the beſt of the bunch (though there are ſome honeſt men amongſt them) and one that would deſerve to be eſteemed a moderate man, (if he would give over his rayling and ſcribling of fooliſh Books againſt the diſſenting-brethren, and men in affliction) of any of theſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes; his anſwer will be; why, ſure it cannot be? my Lieutenant is a Saint, a godly man, &amp; one that never did any man any wrong, no, nor would do it, to gain a world: He is a man that is very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in taking Notes at Sermons, and goes to repetitions often, and does nothing, but what he doth by the Order of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for the ſafety of the Tower; and ſurely, hee is wronged, Which puts us in mind of a merry ſtory we read in the Hiſtory of
<hi>Reynard the Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Vpon a time, the Lyon proclaimed a great Feaſt, and invited all the Beaſts of the Court; amongſt divers beaſts that came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Panther came, and made a great complaint againſt
<hi>Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard the Fox;</hi> which was, that hee had (feyning great devotion) promiſed unto <hi>Kyward the Hare,</hi> to teach him his Creed, and to make him a fit Chaplain for the King, and did ſing <hi>Credo, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> to him: the ſilly Hare believing, the Fox would have kept his promiſe, and have
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aught him to ſing
<hi>Credo,</hi> and become a good Chaplain for his preferment, came between his legs, but he was no ſooner there, but in ſtead of teaching him his
<hi>Credo,</hi> the Fox ſnapt at his throat: and if the Panther had not come in, &amp; reſcued him, the Fox had there devoured the Hare. When this complaint was made, <hi>Grymbard the Brock,</hi> that was <hi>Reynards</hi> ſiſters Son, anſwered for his Unkle,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">My Uncle is a Gentleman, and a true-man, he cannot endure falſhood, he doth nothing without the Councell of his Prieſt, hee <pb n="54" facs="tcp:113893:30"/> eateth but once a day, he liveth as a recluſe, he chaſtiſeth his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and lives only by Almes, and good mens charities, doing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite penance for his ſins; ſo that he is become pale and lean with praying and faſting, for he would fain be in Heaven.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But whileſt <hi>Grymbard</hi> was making this defence, in comes
<hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticleer the Cocke,</hi> clapping his wings with dolefull cry, and accuſed <hi>Reynard</hi> for murthering his faire Daughter <hi>Coppel,</hi> and that hee had eaten her, and that <hi>Grymbard</hi> had eaten the bones which <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> left.</p>
            <p>We promiſe you, Mr. <hi>White,</hi> a ſhrewd evidence againſt <hi>Reynard:</hi> neither, though that <hi>Reynard</hi> pleaded, this was done by adviſe of his prieſt, and was paler and leaner with faſting and praying, then your Lieutenant is; yet it did not excuſe him.</p>
            <p>And you may remember, Mr. <hi>White,</hi> that there is an out-cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lieutenant, that albeit the honourable Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have made an Ordinance, that priſoners in the Tower of <hi>London</hi> ſhould be brought to the Bar of the Kings Bench by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus,</hi> to the end, they might be charged by their Creditors for their juſt debts, and removed to the Kings Bench; Yet the Lieutenant did refuſe to obey an
<hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> in that caſe, upon pretence that there were fees due unto him from the priſoner which was to be removed: and for the ſame, he is ordered, upon a pain, to bring in the priſoner the firſt day of the next Terme, the Judges not allowing that a good plea.</p>
            <p>And as we remember, Mr. <hi>White,</hi> when your wife diſtrained your priſoners Trunk, your Lieutenant awarded the priſoner to pay 4. l. for the redemption to you before he could have it: So that, Mr.
<hi>White,</hi> you playd <hi>Grymbard</hi> here: nor can the Lieutenant free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by ſaying he did theſe things by order of the Committee; for we are confident, that the Committee are perſons of that piety, honour, integrity, &amp; juſtice, that they would not ſtain their names with command of ſuch barbarous tyranny as hath been practiſed againſt the poor priſoners, their Wives, Ladies, and Children in that priſon.</p>
            <p>Therefore, we do aſſoyle them, and leave it at Mr. Lieutenants door, till he plainly and evidently remove it further; And becauſe Mr. Lieutenant, or any that he employes for the guard of his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, may know their duties of their places the more cleerly, and <pb n="55" facs="tcp:113893:30"/> may not pretend ignorance for uſage of their priſoners; we have thought fit to publiſh the Lawes that have reference to Gaolers and Keepers of Priſons: which Lawes, they upon their ſeveral pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties are to obſerve, and the people to preſerve as a main badge of their Liberties, leaſt by the neglect of them; an inſenſible ſlavery be drawn upon them.</p>
            <p>Now, concerning the lawes of priſoners, and the uſage of priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; we find by the common law, <hi>Quod Carcer ad cominendos non ad puniendos haberi debet,</hi> as <hi>Bracton l. 3. f.</hi> 105. Gaoles are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to hold priſoners, not to puniſh them: For, impriſonment by the law, is (neither ought to be) no more then a bare reſtraint of liberty, without thoſe illegall and unjuſt diſtinctions, of cloſe and open priſoner, as appears by <hi>Stamf. pl. Cor. f.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>Yet we know ſome kept cloſe priſoners in the Tower almoſt
3, years, committed only by Warrant of a ſingle Peer, (a moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oppreſſion.)</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Bracton f.</hi> 18. ſaith, That if a Gaoler keepe his priſoner more cloſe then of right he ought, whereof the priſoner dieth; this is Fellony in the Gaoler.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Horn</hi> in the <hi>Mirrour of Juſtice, p.</hi> 288. ſaith, That it is an abuſion of the law that priſoners are put into Irons, or other pain, before they are attainted.</p>
            <p>And p 34. 36. he reckons the ſterving of priſoners by famine, to be among the crimes of homicide in a Gaoler.</p>
            <p>And we find 3. <hi>E. 3. Fitzh. Tit. pl. Cor.</hi> 295. That it was Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony at common law in Gaolers to compel their priſoners by hard impriſonment to become Approvers, whereby to get their goods: which law is ſince confirmed by the ſtatute of 14. <hi>E. 3. c.</hi> 9. with ſome inlargement, as to under-keepers of priſons, and the penalty of the law: and that Gaolers having done this, have been hanged for it; you may read 3. <hi>E.
3. 8. Northampton. Fitzh. pl. Cor.</hi> 295. and elſe-where: but this for a taſte to them. Wee now come to ſhew what fees are due to them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Mirrour of Juſtice, p.</hi> 288. tells us, that it is an abuſion of the law, that priſoners or others for the, to pay any thing for their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries into the Goale, or for their going out: this is the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law; there is no fee due to them by the common law. See what the ſtatutes ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:113893:31"/> The State of <hi>Weſtm. 1. c.</hi> 26. ſaith, that no Sheriffe, or other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the King, ſhall take reward for doing their Offices, but what; they take of the King, if they do: they ſhall forfeit double to the party grieved, and be puniſhed at the will of the King. Under this word Miniſter of the King, are encluded all
<hi>Eſcheators, Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Gaolers, and the like; ſoe Sir Edward Cook 2. part of his Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes, p.</hi> 209. affirms, and agreeable is
<hi>Stamf. pl. Coron.</hi> 49. a. Nay, by the ſtatute of 4. <hi>E. 3. c. 10. Gaolers are to receive theeves and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, taking nothing by way of fees for the receipt of them:</hi> ſo odious is this extortion of Gaolers, <hi>that very theeves and felons are exempt from payment of fees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we find in our Law-bookes, that no fees are due to any Officer, Gaoler, or miniſter of Juſtice, <hi>but only thoſe which are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Act of Parliament:</hi> for if a Gaoler will preſcribe for any fees, the preſcription is void; becauſe againſt this <hi>Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> made 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. being an Act made within time of memory, and takes away all manner of pretended fees, before; and wee are ſure, none can be raiſed by colour of preſcription, ſince: and therefore we find by the bookes of 8. <hi>E. 4. f. 18. That a Marſhall or Gaoler cannot detain any priſoner after his diſcharge from Court, but only for the fees of the Court,</hi> the Court being not barred by this ſtatute of
<hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. afore-mentioned; and if he doe, he may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted of extortion; and agrecable to this, is the book of 21. <hi>H. 7. f.</hi> 16. where amongſt other things, it is held for law, that if a Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler or Guardian of a priſon, takes his priſoners upper garment, Cloak, or money from him; it is a treſpaſſe, and the Gaoler ſhall be anſwerable for it: (this is a note for the Gentleman-Porter of the Tower) ſo that we may undeniably conclude, that there is no fee at all due to any Gaoler or Guardian of a priſon, from the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (but what is due unto him by ſpeciall Act of Parliament.) And if a Gaoler or Guardian of a Priſon ſhall take any thing as a fee of his priſoner, he may, and ought to be indicted of extortion, and upon conviction, to be removed from his office; And if his priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by conſtraint, menaſſe, or dures, be enforced to give him mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he may recover that money againſt the Gaoler again, in an Action of the caſe, to be brought againſt him as his Bayliffe <hi>per accompt rendre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is fit to be remembred alſo, that whileſt priſoners are in <pb n="57" facs="tcp:113893:31"/> cuſtody, having nothing of their own to maintain them, being ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſpoyled of their eſtates or goods by plunder, ſequeſtration, long lying in priſon, or otherwiſe;
<q rend="margQuotes">That the priſoners in all the Kings priſons ſhould be maintained at the Kings charge, &amp; out of the Kings Revenues, according to the old law of the Land.</q> 
               <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaid thus, <hi>Priſones impriſonati; antequam convicti fuerint, de terris ſuis deſſeiſiri non debent; nes de rebus ſuis quibuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſpoliari: ſed, dum fuerint in priſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; debent de proprio in omnibus ſuſtentari, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo per judicium deliberati vel condemnati fuerint;</hi> which we Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thus, Priſoners detained in priſon, ought not to be diſſeiſed, or put out of their lands and free-holds, nor ſpoyled of their goods before they be convicted: but, they ought to be maintained of their own goods and eſtates in all things they want, untill by judgment they are either acquitted or convicted. Nay, we ſay further, that if priſoners have not whereof, of their own to live; theyought to be maintained, according to their qualities, out of the Kings revenue, and at his charge, whoſe priſoners they are; and this is according to the fundamentall lawes of the Land, and is a liberty inheritable, belonging to the free-born ſubjects of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> but if wee look into the priſons of theſe ſaid times; Oh! what horrible oppreſſions, extortions, cruelties, and moſt unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-like tyrannies are exerciſed and practiſed upon the free-born ſubjects of, <hi>England</hi> in all priſons within the kingdome, by theſe ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> theſe ravening Harpies, and tormenting Gaolers, whom we may properly call the Divels Deputies, that rack even the very bowels, and feed upon the very livers of their priſoners, ſucking away the very blood that ſhould give life to their bodies, from them; what lamentable cryes, ſighes, and groanes, doe wee hear from every corner of this kingdome; eſpecially of this City, from the poor, ſtarved, oppreſſed, life-wearied priſoners, ſhut up &amp; incloſed in the Dungeons and Priſons in all places? What horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lamentations, imprecations, and curſes are uttered, and ſent up to God Almighty, in anguiſh of mind, and bitterneſſe of ſpirit, by theſe poor priſoners, their wives and children not onely againſt their tormenting Gaolers, but alſo againſt thoſe Prieſts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy politique, thoſe Country-Committees, who have turned the wives and children of poor priſoners a begging, and ſent them up to ſterve in Priſons and Dungeons, under the hands of mercileſſe <pb n="58" facs="tcp:113893:32"/> Gaolers, with their diſtreſſed Husbands and Parents, having not only their goods and free-holds taken away from them; which by law ſhould be their ſupport in priſon: but what alſo they beg or borrow, is extorted from them by theſe ravening, mercileſſe, and oppreſſing Gaolers, and their Miniſters.</p>
            <p>We therefore, the free-born people of <hi>England,</hi> having ſeriouſly weighed and conſidered with our ſelves; that by theſe lordly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and ſentences executed upon us by that ſentence of the houſe of Peers upon Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> a free-born Engliſh-man, and one that hath ſo often with his ſword in his hand for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and reviving of our declining liberties, adventured his lite in the field againſt the Royall intruders, and out of hatred and deteſtation to the execrable and odious oppreſſions of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Gaolers and other inferiour Miniſters of this preſent State, having an earneſt deſire and reſolution to enjoyour liberties, which with our deareſt bloods, and with the loſſe of ſo many lives of our dear brethren, and vaſt expence of treaſure wee have purchaſed; and being of nothing ſo much affected and enamoured, as to live under the happy and flouriſhing eſtate of this ever renowned Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the moſt honourable Commons, whom we have choſen &amp; intruſted for us to ſit at <hi>Westm.</hi> as Guardians of our Birth-rights, and moſt powerfull Tribunes of the peoples liberties, and who have made ſo many pious and feeling Declarations of their mindes now in print, concerning our by-paſt thraldome, with moſt ſolemn Proteſtations, and execrations upon themſelves, of their ſerious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, <hi>to maintain the lawes and liberties of the free-born Subjects of England,</hi> and that <hi>SALVS POPVLI</hi> ſhall be to them, their
<hi>SVPREMA LEX,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet out of our dayly feeling of our enſuing miſeries, &amp; a cleere fore-ſight of a future and ſpeedy ruine of this preſent State (which above all thingsunder heaven we deſire to advance) if it be not by the wiſdome of theſe our moſt honoured Patriots prevented; doe moſt humbly addreſſe our informations of the grievances &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evils, and advices for reformation of the ſame, <hi>to our moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Trustees;</hi> not doubting, but they in their profound wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, will both receive them benignely, prudently ponder them, and ſeriouſly and timely endeavour to prevent the growing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, by their indulgent and ſerious care and circumſpection: <hi>To <pb n="59" facs="tcp:113893:32"/> you then, Oh! you moſt honourable Tribunes of the People, preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Common-wealth, and chief Guardians of our Laws &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties) we apply our ſelves as next under God, the ſureſt Inſtruments of our earthly felicity;</hi> And, we do moſt humbly implore &amp; beſeech you to free us from all lordly, illegall ſentences, and tyrannicall powers and executions whatſoever: wee intreat and exhort you to hear and determine Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburns</hi> appeale to you the Commons repreſentative of <hi>England</hi> from the Lords houſe; we will not preſume to direct you, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is fit to be determined in it, for we neither can nor will diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt, either your Judgment or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: but this we humbly beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ech you to conſider, <hi>that in your judgment upon him ſhall be involved the liberty of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England: and think it not a Trouble to your ſelves to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunedin this particular,</hi> but give ſpeedy diſpatch therein to your Petitioners, ſince that a Republique that is well ordered, ought to give eaſie acceſſe to thoſe that ſeek Juſtice by publique meanes.</p>
            <p>In the next place, our deſires are, that ſince this great inrode up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our liberty, is occaſioned by an Impeachment or Accuſation made in your houſe againſt Col. <hi>King,</hi> which yet there depends undetermined; that you would hear and determine that Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and bring the Offendor to condigne puniſhment, and not only Col. <hi>King,</hi> but all others whom you haue truſted in this late War, and have fayled in their truſt: What though the war ſeeme to be at an end, and you have effected your deſires, and theſe men have at ſome time ſtood you inſtead, and at firſt proved faithfull and were ſtrongly aſſiſtant to you; yet, if afterwards they proved corrupt or negligent, or falſified there truſt, ſhould they therefore be pardoned? put the caſe, a new war ſhould break out, and you ſhould have need of men: think you, that thoſe you ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter employ, will not take courage by the impunity of theſe that are now accuſed, to deceive and betray you when they finde opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? Or, do you imagine, that theſe men can ever be faithfull to you? We give you theſe Reaſons, that they cannot.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe they are at leaſt under a ſuſpition; and if they are innocent; why have they been ſo long kept from clearing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? If they be acquitted, and innocent perſons, it is an injury they will never forgive you; and if they be found guilty; you will never truſt them: But ſome will ſay, that they have been good
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113893:33"/> members, and done good ſervice; therefore they ought to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. To which we anſwer, Let them be firſt tryed, and if they are found guilty, uſe your diſcretions in mercy toward them: but withall, remember, that the wiſeſt and beſt governed States in the world, never yet pardoned any man for a notorious crime com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Common-wealth, for any good ſervices before done to it:</p>
            <p>This is manifeſt by many examples; eſpecially in the
<hi>Romane State:</hi> The firſt we will preſent you with, is that of
<hi>Horatius,</hi> where the caſe is thus: <hi>Tullus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> King, and <hi>Metius</hi> the <hi>Alban</hi> King, made an agreement between them, that three of the <hi>Horatii, Romans,</hi> and three of the <hi>Curatii, Albans,</hi> ſhould fight for the Dominion of their Countries; and that, that people whoſe three Champions vanquiſhed the others, ſhould bee Lords of the vanquiſhed Nation; The three <hi>Horatii</hi> got the victory, and but one of them ſurvived in it; all the <hi>Curatii</hi> were ſlaine.
<hi>Horatius</hi> that ſurvived, and was Victor, returning to <hi>Rome,</hi> met his ſiſter, the Widow of one of the <hi>Curatii,</hi> lamenting the death of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, &amp; killed her: <hi>This fact was adjudged ſo heynous,</hi> that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the victory he obtained for the
<hi>Romans,</hi> they brought him to judgement. <hi>Manlius Capitolinus,</hi> notwithſtanding that hee had valiantly defended the <hi>Capitoll of Rome</hi> againſt the invading <hi>Gaules,</hi> and by his vertue delivered the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> from immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger; was, notwithſtanding his good deſerts, for a ſedition he endeavoured to raiſe in <hi>Rome</hi> through envie to <hi>Furius Camillus,</hi> thrown headlong down from that
<hi>Capitoll,</hi> which he to his great renown had formerly defended. So we in
<hi>Machiavel</hi> his diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon <hi>Liv. l. 1. cap.</hi> 23. 24.
26. More examples we might find in the <hi>Roman State,</hi> as thoſe of
<hi>Coriolanus, Martius Livius, Aemilius,</hi> and <hi>Scipio Africanus;</hi> of whoſe Stories you may read at large in <hi>Livies Decades.</hi> We read likewiſe of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> the <hi>Athenian Generall,</hi> and who was a chiefe meants to augment the glory of that State by the great defeat he gave to the <hi>Perſians</hi> at <hi>Salamis,</hi> and elſwhere; having committed offences againſt that Government, had the puniſhment of
<hi>Oſtraciſme,</hi> which was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ten yeares inflicted upon him. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> likewiſe, after many notable victories obtained for that State, was notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding for inſolencies, as they conceived, committed towards it, <pb n="61" facs="tcp:113893:33"/> twice baniſhed: the laſt time, into perpetuall baniſhment. Theſe two examples we find in the State of
<hi>Athens.</hi> We might produce many more, of ancient time, of all the States of <hi>Greece;</hi> which, for Brevity ſake. we omit. Only mentioning ſome, of latter times, in our own neighbourhoods: As, that of <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, who for offence given, ruined <hi>Ferdinandus Cortes</hi> that ſubdued to his obedience and uſe, the mighty rich kingdomes of <hi>Mexico, Jucatan,</hi> and other parts of the <hi>Weſt Indies:</hi> Neither did
<hi>Marſhal Byron,</hi> for all his ſervice done to King <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. of <hi>France,</hi> find at his death any merits in thoſe ſervices done to his offended Prince: Nor, <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevelt</hi> in his conſpiracy againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and State of <hi>Holland,</hi> though he had been eminent for former ſervices done them againſt the Kingof <hi>Spain:</hi> Nor, in our own Kingdom, could <hi>Sir John Hotham</hi> and his ſons former deſerts, ſave their lives, which they loſt for being falſe to the truſt.</p>
            <p>By which examples we conclude, That never any Republick well ordered, cancelled the faults of their ſubject, swith their good deſerts. Therefore as <hi>Clemens Edmunds</hi> obſerves upon <hi>Caeſars Commentaries, p. 174. It more importeth a common-wealth, to puniſh an ill member, then to reward a good act.</hi> Wee alſo affirm, that a State, or a Common-wealth, that will keep it ſelfe in good order, and free from ruine;
<hi>Muſt cheriſh impeachments and accuſations of the people againſt thoſe that through ambition, avarice, pride, cruelty, or oppreſſion, ſeeke to deſtroy the liberty or property of the people:</hi> So ſhall they keep their Eſtate free from envie, and ſecure from ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation: for it is an efficacious meanes to continue the people in a faire obſequency, to parlie often with them upon their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and to provide ſpeedy and proper remedies. We therefore humbly deſire you to take into your ſerious conſiderations, the great oppreſſions committed by theſe
<hi>Countrey-Committees,</hi> who thinke there is no better way to govern the kingdome, then by <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thoſe Concubines of Sovereignty, Tyranny and Arbitrary go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> as <hi>Abſolom</hi> did with his fathers. Theſe <hi>Horſe-leeches of the Common-wealth,</hi> who hang upon the limbs of it, and will continue ſucking out the blood of the poore Countries, till their bellies are full: and then like
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and unprofitable vermin, will fall off your ſervice, to their own ruſe. If you think to bind thoſe people to you by the oppreſſive profits of their places; you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113893:34"/> 
               <hi>For, benefits bind not the covetous, but the honeſt:</hi> and thoſe that are but greedy of themſelves, do in all changes of fortune, only conſult the preſervation of their own greatneſſe. Beſides, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency will attend their actions; that by making a few rich, you undoe multitudes, and loſe the hearts of many, that by clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy may be gained, <hi>to inrich a few by rapine,</hi> that when they are grown wealthy, will think of nothing more then to preſerve their ill-gotten treaſure, and will never venture (when neceſſity challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it) one drop of blood in your cauſe. We ſpeak not this out of any affection to the Royall party; but out of our hatred and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation to oppreſſion and rapine, it being the onely meanes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow this State: For it is moſt certain, that theſe people are eaſily drawn into Commontion, who by their poverty are aſſured to loſe nothing; being by nature alwayes deſirous of innovation. <hi>Wherefore we heartily wiſh the ſuppreſſion of thoſe ravenous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, as utterly deſtructive to the peace and aſſurance of the preſent State and Government.</hi> But if they ſhall ſay in defence of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that they onely poll the Royall parly, and ſuch as have been in Armes againſt the Parl we wiſh they were ſo innocent as they pretend rhemſelves, &amp; that they would pay the Souldiers better, &amp; cleare their accounts to their maſters that have imployed them: which, when they ſhall effect, they ſhall receive our better opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and till that time, they muſt be content to labour under their crying accuſations. But admitting their objection to be true; yet we are of opinion, that courteous and charitable acts, work much more in mens minds that are ſubdued, then thoſe that are full of violence, cruelty &amp; hoſtility. For <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Mitius imperanti me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius paretur,</hi> they are beſt obeyed, that govern moſt mildly. And
<hi>Machiavel ubi ſupra, p.</hi> 542. obſerves, that one act of humanity was of more force with the conquered <hi>Faliſci,</hi> then many violent acts of hoſtility. Therefore we wiſh theſe eager Committe-men to conſider for the good of the State they pretend to ſerve, that it is commodious for thoſe that lay the foundation of a new State, or Soveraignty, to have the fame of being juſt and mercifull: For as Juſtice and Clemency in good Princes or Soveraignes, are the beſt meanes to keep the ſubject faſt bound unto them in obedience and duties; ſo are cruelty, oppreſſion and rage, bridles wherewith ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants keep their ſubjects in awe and ſubjection unto them, and <pb n="63" facs="tcp:113893:34"/> themſelves in their eſtates. And let theſe Committee-men ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their actions in ſcrewing the Countries, that they ſow not a jealouſie among the free-born people of
<hi>England,</hi> that they intend to hold up that common Maxime of all oppreſſing States, which is, <hi>That their intereſt is to maintain the publick, wealthy, and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular poore;</hi> which if once the common people apprehend, they are not long to bee held in obedience: For where a
<hi>State</hi> holds their ſubjects under the condition of ſlaves, the conqueſt thereof is eaſie, and ſoon aſſured. <hi>And when a forced Government ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in ſtrength, it will ſuffer as did the old Lion for the opprſſion done in his youth, being pinched by the Wolf, goared by the Bull, and kickt alſo by the Aſſe,</hi> as Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh l.
5. fol.</hi> 501. wittily obſerves. And then when it is too late, they complain of their hard fortune; for ſorrow can give remedy to miſchiefes paſt, and anger is vaine where there wants forces to revenge. <hi>Correct thoſe mercileſſe ſons of Cerberus, thoſe greedy Goalers exceſſive demands, and extortions of fees from their diſtreſſed priſoners.</hi> Suffer not that vengeance which the complaints and groanes of thoſe miſerable and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoules will draw down from the moſt juſt God for this kind of oppreſſion; to fell upon your heads, by your connivence at, and tolleration of, their exactions. And if that cannot move you, yet let us adviſe you, not to permit them to create Preſidents of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to enſlave your poſterity in future times. <hi>For who knowes what a day may bring forth? There is no new thing under the Sun.</hi> Therefore there is no confidence to be had in our preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſince, as the Preacher tells us, <hi>Eccleſ. 1. 4. One generation paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and another cometh, but the earth endureth for ever.</hi> Be juſt and mercifull therefore, <hi>O yee Rulers and Judges of the earth, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that for all theſe things you ſhall one day be brought to judgment.</hi> And this conſideration prompts us further to intreat and implore you to keep and obſerve the known, written, and promulged laws of this land: if you keep them, they will keep you. <hi>Aboliſh and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon, as an infectious diſeaſe to your State, all arbitrary power, and diſcretionary government, in prerogative times falſly called, the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiall way.</hi> There is nothing of worſe example in a Republick, then to have good lawes, and not to obſerve them. <hi>Good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment procures love from the Subject:</hi> and it is onely their love that ſupports a State in time of adverſity. The Nations that endure <pb n="64" facs="tcp:113893:35"/> the worſt under their own Governours, are not greatly fearfull of a forraign yoak: whereas men when they are well governed, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeek after other liberty. <hi>That government is of all moſt ſure, where the people take joy in their obedience,</hi> The <hi>Samnits</hi> rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Romanes, becauſe Peace was more grievous to them in ſubjection, then War to thoſe that enjoy their liberty; <hi>And on the contrary, Petillia a City of the Brutians in Italy, choſe rather to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all extremity of War from Hanniball, then upon any condition to forſake the Romanes, who had governed them moderately, and by that good government procured their love: yea, even at the time when the Romanes ſent them word, they were not able to relieve them, wiſhing them to provide for their own ſafety,</hi> as we read, <hi>Livy Decad. 1. l.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Therefore, it never turnes to a States advantage; to gaine the peoples hatred: the way to avoid it, is to lay no hands on the Subjects eſtates.</p>
            <p>How many flouriſhing States have been ruined by the Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, Pride, Cruelty, and non-obſervance of the lawes by the Governours?</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Athens</hi> being ſore urged with a War by
<hi>Darius</hi> from <hi>Perſia;</hi> in their great diſtreſſe, choſe
<hi>Critias Theramenes,,</hi> &amp; 28. others, to be their Governours. They were elected firſt to compile a body of their Law, and put in practiſe ſuch antient Statutes, as were fit to be put in practiſe: to this charge was annexed the ſupream Authority, either as a recompence of their labours, or becauſe the neceſſity of time required it.</p>
            <p>Theſe Governours, in ſtead of making or obſerving the laws, fell to ſpoyle the people of their lives and goods, by new lawes and arbitrary proceedings; this was hatefull to the people: the end was,
<hi>Thraſibulus</hi> and 70. others conſpired againſt them, and cut them off, and reſtored the people to their former liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The Governour of the
<hi>Eleans</hi> held a ſtrict hand over their Subjects, and oppreſſed them: The Subjects being in deſpaire, called in the <hi>Spartans</hi> to their reliefe, who had no juſt cauſe of quarrell, but only an old grudge; and by their help freed all their Cities from the ſharp bondage of their naturall Lords.</p>
            <p>The Eſtate of <hi>Sparta</hi> was grown powerfull, and oppreſt the <hi>Thebans:</hi> The <hi>Thebans,</hi> though but a weak State, yet deſperate of their ſuffering; by the help of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> found means to free <pb n="65" facs="tcp:113893:35"/> themſelves of their cruell yoke.</p>
            <p>Theſe examples, and divers others, we finde of the fall of the free Eſtates of <hi>Greece,</hi> recorded by Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> in his 3. book of the <hi>Hiſtory of the world.</hi> The forceable cauſes of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the State of <hi>Carthage</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi> (which once contended with <hi>Rome</hi> for the Dominion and Soveraignty of the World) were Avarice and Cruelty. Their Avarice (ſaith <hi>Regius)</hi> was ſhewed, both in exacting from their Subjects, (beſides ordinary Tributes) the one half of the profits of the earth, and in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Offices not upon Gentlemen, and mercifull perſons; but upon thoſe who could beſt tyrannize over the people to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their treaſures. Their cruelty appeared, in putting men to death without mercy or juſtice, contrary to their Lawes. Wee read in <hi>Guicciardine,</hi> that <hi>Piſa</hi> revolted from, and maintained 10. years ſharp Wars againſt, the State of <hi>Florence,</hi> and would not ſubmit to her yoke, by reaſon of the hard impoſitions laid upon her by the <hi>Florentines,</hi> but choſe rather to put her ſelf under pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12. of <hi>France,</hi> a forraign and an hard maſter. We know that an impoſition of the tenth penny upon the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Holland,</hi> and the execution of arbitrary government by the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> loſt the Dominion of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> to
<hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Spain.</hi> Wee could tell of the often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volts of <hi>Genoa</hi> from the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> of
<hi>Siena, Lacquis, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena, Regia, Vincenſa, Padua, Crimona, Millain, and other Towns, and Provinces of Italy, from the States whereon they have depended,</hi> even from <hi>Venice</hi> (that only free State well governed in the world) by reaſon of the avarice, cruelty, pride, and injuſtice of their Governours.</p>
            <p>We could tell you, how the Duke <hi>Valentinois,</hi> or
<hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> loſt his new Conqueſts in <hi>Italy,</hi> by his pride and cruelty over the vanquiſht people.</p>
            <p>We could remember, how <hi>Alphonſo</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> Kings of <hi>Naples,</hi> loſt their dominions and lives, by their extream tyranny over the Nobility, Gentry, and Subjects of their Realm.</p>
            <p>We could tell you, how the <hi>Syracuſians, Leontines,</hi> and
<hi>Meſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and other States of <hi>Sicillie</hi> were ſtripped of their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and fell into the hands of their neighbours the
<hi>Romanes,</hi> by their great cruelty to their own Subjects. Wee could find parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <pb n="66" facs="tcp:113893:36"/> inſtances and examples, in all Empires, Kingdomes, and free States that have been ſince the Creation of the World; that the Princes and Governours, for their tyrannie, and not due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Lawes of their Countries, have been baniſhed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, and put to death by their Subjects.</p>
            <p>Ye know well enough, that <hi>Rehoboam</hi> loſt 10. Tribes for an harſh anſwer to a petioning people, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 9.</p>
            <p>We could give you ſome Scriptual-examples of free-States; but that we find none mentioned there; but conclude, that there was never any State, more glorious, more free, more carefull of preſerving it ſelf, then that of <hi>Rome;</hi> and yet ſhe fell too, and never recovered her former libertie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanes,</hi> out of a fore-ſight that her ruine would come upon her by the oppreſſion and avarice of her Governours, made a Law,
<hi>de repetundis,</hi> or of recovery againſt extorting Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; yet it ſerved not to reſtrain their Provinciall Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, though it relieved the Citizens at home, which was one of the two cauſes of <hi>Romes</hi> ruine: for, as <hi>Machiavel</hi> in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes upon <hi>Livy, l. 3. c.</hi> 34. obſerves, that theſe two things were the cauſes of that Republiques diſſolution; the one was, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which grew upon the
<hi>Agearian</hi> Law, or partition of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Land among the Citizens: the other was, the prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Governments, <hi>viz. Dictatorſhips, Conſulſhips, Generalſhips, Tribuneſhips</hi> of the people, and ſuch like great Offices: for, by theſe meanes, thoſe great Officers had meanes and power to raiſe armes againſt the liberty of the people: <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Marius</hi> by this meanes could find Souldiers to take their part againſt the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique; and <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> could find meanes hereby to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Lord of his native Country and Country-men.</p>
            <p>Theſe things we alleadge not, as if we ſuſpected any of you, (O ye noble <hi>Patriots)</hi> to be guilty of any of theſe crimes, that may either hazard the continuing of the preſent Government, or deſtroy the publike liberty; but to awake you, and put you in mind to provide fit remedies againſt theſe growing evills, whereby you may procure ſafety and peace to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and everlaſting honour to your own Names and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; for they are to be thought worthy of honour, not which begin, but well end honourable Actions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:113893:36"/> And we beſeech you, not to take it in ill part from us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we offer our humble advices to you in theſe particulars;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce we the people, conceive it our duty, to ſhew unto our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, that good, which by reaſon of the malignity of the times and of fortune, we have not been able to do our ſelves; to the end, that you our Senators, being given to underſtand thereof, ſome of you whom God ſhall more favour, may put it in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe for the publike good.</p>
            <p>Neither is our opinion to be deſpiſed: For it is a ſure Maxime, that the people are of as clear judgment in all things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Publique, as any, and is wiſe, and circumſpect concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their liberties, and are as capable of the truth they heare. We know that Common-wealths have never been much ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, neither in dominion nor riches,
<hi>unleſſe only during their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> for it is no mans particular good that amplifies the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. We know that thoſe that haue in their hands the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a State, ought to increaſe the number of their free Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>and make them as their Aſſociates, and not Vaſſals.</hi> We know that it is more honourable and profitable unto a State, moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to uſe their Subjects meanes, thereby to keep their State in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity, then through covetouſneſſe to devoure them in one day, and in their loſſe to undoe themſelves for ever. We know that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie</hi> is a violent forme of Government, not reſpecting the good of the Subjects, but only the pleaſure of the Commanders. <hi>We know that it is better to live under an hard and harſh known written law, where every man may read his duty, and know his offence, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; then under the mildeſt arbitrary government, where the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is condemned at the will of their Judges, without any certain or known Rules, how ſpecious or juſt ſoever the pretence of this kind of proceeding may be.</hi> Wee know that the pretence of neceſſity in a Prince or State, <hi>is but the Bawde to Tyrannie;</hi> And, that Tyrannie is more odious in a State we deſire to maintain by love, then in a Prince that ſeekes to bring it upon his Subjects by force. Wee know, that thoſe States, that <hi>call all the endeavours of their ſubjects, only duty and debt,</hi> and are more apt to oppreſſe their people, then to do them Juſtice, ſhall find themſelves upon the firſt change of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, not only the moſt friendl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, but even the moſt contemptible and deſpiſed of all other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:113893:37"/> And we fear, that notwithſtanding all our deſires of the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of this State; there will be little amended, till by ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, the truth of our conjectures in the hazard of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, are made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>For we know, that all men are better taught by their owne er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, then by the examples of their fore-goers: but if our earneſt deſires and humble ſupplications, ſhall either with ſcorn be reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or with negligence diſregarded, to the apparent hazard of the publike liberty, and moſt deſirable State we wiſh to ſupport; we hope that God will raiſe up ſome noble Engliſh Romane Spirit, ſuch a one as <hi>Caius Flaminius,</hi> who as Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh l. 5. p.</hi> 357. obſerves, for the preſervation and maintenance of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,
<hi>underſtanding the Majeſty of Rome to be wholly in the people, and no otherwiſe in the Senate, then by way of delegacy, or grand Commiſſion, did not ſtand highly upon his birth and degree, but aſſiſted the Multitude, and taught them to know and uſe their power over himſelf, and his fellow-Senators, in reforming their diſorders; and vindicating the publike liberty of his Countrey:</hi> In, and for which, we are reſolved to dye: and which we wiſh may alwayes flouriſh, and continue for the perpetuall benefit, utility, and renown of all the free-born Subjects of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:113893:37"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader, in regard Lieu. Colonel <hi>Lilburns</hi> Charge and Sentence in the Lords Houſe, and their Orders thereupon, are not as yet in any Book printed, but in this <hi>Vox Plebis;</hi> although there is, in ſeveral Books, much of his cruel uſage, by vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; publiſhed: I ſhall deſire thee to read his own two Books, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Londons Liberty in Chains diſcovered,</hi> printed <hi>Octob.</hi> 1646. And his <hi>Anatomy of the Lords Tyranny and Injuſtice exerciſed upon him;</hi> printed
<hi>Novemb.</hi> 9. 1646. which two compared with this, doe fully and amply declare and prove all the Lords proceedings with him to be moſt illegall and unjuſt. And as thou readeſt the fore-going Diſcourſe; with thy Pen amend theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Preſſe-faults.</p>
            <p>Pag. 2. line firſt, (for <hi>irepairable,</hi> read
<hi>irreparable.)</hi> p. 4. l. 15 (for <hi>as protected,</hi> read <hi>is protected.</hi> and l. 37. for <hi>Marrow of Iuſtice</hi> read <hi>Mirror of Iuſtice.)</hi> p. 6. l. 5. for <hi>their ſubiects,</hi> read <hi>the ſubiects.)</hi> p. 9. l. 32. for <hi>contentment</hi> read
<hi>contenement.</hi> page 12. l. 19. for <hi>May 16. H.</hi> 6. read <hi>Mich.
16. H.</hi> 6. p. 15. l. 28. read <hi>outlawed but by.</hi> p. 16. l. 20. for
<hi>aed</hi> read <hi>and</hi> p. 17. l. 14. for <hi>dye</hi> read
<hi>dine.</hi> p. 18. which ſhould be p. 20. l. 9. for <hi>vinvocally</hi> read <hi>univerſally.</hi> p. 21. l. 18. for <hi>torvous</hi> read
<hi>torcious.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. l.
27. for <hi>witneſſes</hi> read <hi>Writs.</hi> l. 34. <hi>for Aſtutia</hi> read <hi>Atia.</hi> p. 24. l. 4. for <hi>rediendo</hi> read
<hi>redeundo.</hi> p. 28. l. 4. &amp; 5. read <hi>in intereſt</hi> for <hi>in in intereſt.</hi> l. 25. for <hi>inflame</hi> read <hi>inſlave.</hi> p. 29. l. 10. for <hi>improved</hi> read <hi>impowered.</hi> p. 30. l. 1. read
<hi>concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> for <hi>concerning.</hi> p. 37. l. 17. read <hi>quod</hi> for <hi>quid.</hi> p. 47. l. 7. read <hi>queſtion</hi> for
<hi>queſtiſtion.</hi> p. 57. l. 35. read <hi>peſts</hi> for
<hi>Prieſts.</hi> p. 62. l. 12. read <hi>the people</hi> for <hi>theſe people,</hi> l. 13. read <hi>commotion</hi> for <hi>commonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> p. 63. l.
14. for <hi>can give remedy</hi> read <hi>can give no remedy.</hi> p. 66. l.
21. for the <hi>Agearian law</hi> read <hi>Agrarian law.</hi> p. 67. l. 11: for
<hi>conceive the publick;</hi> read <hi>concern the publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
